[
  {
    "questionNum": 72001,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Kapal Kundala”?",
    "answerText": " Bankim Chandra Chatterjee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72002,
    "questionText": " Excessive intake of polished rice causes deficiency of which vitamin ?",
    "answerText": " B1 (Thiamine)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72003,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Wake up India ?",
    "answerText": " Annie Besant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72004,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “To Each His Stranger”?",
    "answerText": " S H Vatsyayan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72005,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of ‘My South Block Years‘?",
    "answerText": " J.N. Dixit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72006,
    "questionText": " Agra is on the bank of which River?",
    "answerText": " Jamuna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72007,
    "questionText": " First Indian girl to win the British Junior Squash title?",
    "answerText": " Joshna Chinappa (17 yrs)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72008,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Makers of Modern India ?",
    "answerText": " Ramachandra Guha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72009,
    "questionText": " Which place is known as the Land of Gods?",
    "answerText": " Kasargode"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72010,
    "questionText": " Bangladesh was separated from Pakistan in?",
    "answerText": " March 26;1971"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72011,
    "questionText": " Demosthenese was a well known orator from?",
    "answerText": " Greek"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72012,
    "questionText": " How many nations signed he UN Charter at San Francisco?",
    "answerText": " Fifty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72013,
    "questionText": " Who was known as ‘the prince among the humanists’?",
    "answerText": " Erasmus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72014,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Yanthram”?",
    "answerText": " Malayattoor Ramakrishnan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72015,
    "questionText": " Tuberculosis is also known as ?",
    "answerText": " 'White Plague.'"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72016,
    "questionText": " Indian Institute of Science is located at?",
    "answerText": " Bangalore."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72017,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Many worlds; Yesterday and Today”?",
    "answerText": " K.P.S Menon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72018,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Shahnama?",
    "answerText": " Firdausi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72019,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Indira - The Life of Indira Nehru and Gandhi?",
    "answerText": " Katerine Frank"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72020,
    "questionText": " James D Watson and Francis Crick were awarded Nobel Prize in 1962 for the discovery of ?",
    "answerText": " DNA in 1953"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72021,
    "questionText": " 17th Parallel separates?",
    "answerText": " North and South Vietnam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72022,
    "questionText": " Who invented Mule in 1779?",
    "answerText": " Samuel Crompton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72023,
    "questionText": " Largest Bird?",
    "answerText": " Ostrich"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72024,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Electrons?",
    "answerText": " J.J.Thomson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72025,
    "questionText": " Cochin University of Science and Technology was founded in?",
    "answerText": 1971
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72026,
    "questionText": " Which is the disease that affects largest number of people in the world?",
    "answerText": " Common cold"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72027,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Naryaneeyam?",
    "answerText": " Melpathur Bhattathiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72028,
    "questionText": " Who was the first to become Chief Minister after holding the post of Speaker?",
    "answerText": " C.H. Muhammed Koya."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72029,
    "questionText": " Longest Poem of the World?",
    "answerText": " Mahabaratha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72030,
    "questionText": " China’s Sorrow?",
    "answerText": " River Hwang Ho"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72031,
    "questionText": " Hydathodes occur on .?",
    "answerText": " Leaves"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72032,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Himalayan Blunder Brig”?",
    "answerText": " J P Dalvi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72033,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Love in the time of Cholera”?",
    "answerText": " Gabriel Garcia Marquez"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72034,
    "questionText": " Chromosome is made up of ?",
    "answerText": " DNA & Proteins"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72035,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Pratham Pratishruti ?",
    "answerText": " Ashapurna Devi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72036,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The White Tiger”?",
    "answerText": " Arvind Adiga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72037,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Ninteen Eighty Four?",
    "answerText": " George Orwell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72038,
    "questionText": " Longest Road?",
    "answerText": " P a n - A m e r i c a n Highway 27387 km (North West Alaska to Southern most Chile)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72039,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Museum of Innocence”?",
    "answerText": " Orhan Pamuk"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72040,
    "questionText": " Which is the first Asian country to launch a space shuttle?",
    "answerText": " China"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72041,
    "questionText": " Heart beats in adults is ?",
    "answerText": " 72 per minute"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72042,
    "questionText": " Where was the first Jews Synagogue in Kerala built?",
    "answerText": " Mattancherry."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72043,
    "questionText": " Lenin was born in ?",
    "answerText": " 1870 April 10 in Simbrisk; Russia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72044,
    "questionText": " Who introduced Five Year Plans (1928) for the economic progress of Russia?",
    "answerText": " Stalin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72045,
    "questionText": " Which is the supreme organ of the WTO?",
    "answerText": " The Ministerial Council"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72046,
    "questionText": " When established Kerala Kalamandalam was situated in?",
    "answerText": " Cheruthuruthi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72047,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Czechoslovakia?",
    "answerText": " Prague (Praha)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72048,
    "questionText": " Aristotle was the famous student of?",
    "answerText": " Plato"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72049,
    "questionText": " Largest bird is?",
    "answerText": " North African Ostrich"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72050,
    "questionText": " The Royal symbol of the Pandyas was?",
    "answerText": " Fish."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72051,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Bird of Time?",
    "answerText": " Sarojini Naidu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72052,
    "questionText": " Who was the publisher of Vijnanachinthamani, the first Sankrit news paper?",
    "answerText": " Punnasheri Neelakanda Sharma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72053,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Agni Veena”?",
    "answerText": " Kazi Nazrul Islam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72054,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Men Who Kept Secrets”?",
    "answerText": " Thomas Powers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72055,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of The Bell Jar?",
    "answerText": " Sylvia Plath"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72056,
    "questionText": " Largest in Area?",
    "answerText": " Russia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72057,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of ‘Chemmeen’?",
    "answerText": " Thakazhi Sivasankara Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72058,
    "questionText": " Nehru Trophy is associated with?",
    "answerText": " Hockey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72059,
    "questionText": " …..is the sort of a speculator; who stands to gain with a rise in the price of shares and stocks?",
    "answerText": " Bull"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72060,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “A Secular Agenda”?",
    "answerText": " Arun Shourie"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72061,
    "questionText": " What is the name of the Indian military operation in Kargil to expel the ussurpers?",
    "answerText": " 'Operation Vijay' of 1999"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72062,
    "questionText": " Herodotus who is considered as the Father of History was a great ?",
    "answerText": " Greek historian who wrote about Persian War"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72063,
    "questionText": " Which sea is the western boundary of Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Lakshdweep sea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72064,
    "questionText": " Which is the capital of Falkland Island?",
    "answerText": " Stanley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72065,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Pathumayude Aadu”?",
    "answerText": " Vaikom Muhammed Basheer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72066,
    "questionText": " Which is known as the first Sankrit news paper?",
    "answerText": " Vijnanachinthamani"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72067,
    "questionText": " Alexander defeated the Persian ruler ?",
    "answerText": " Darius Ill"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72068,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Macbeth ?",
    "answerText": " William Shakespeare"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72069,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Da VinciCode”?",
    "answerText": " Dan Brown"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72070,
    "questionText": " Which organ controls reflex actions in human beings?",
    "answerText": " The spinal cord"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72071,
    "questionText": " From which language the word 'Chemistry' was originated?",
    "answerText": " The Egyptian language"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72072,
    "questionText": " Cobalt-60 is used in treatment of which disease?",
    "answerText": " Cancer."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72073,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Israel?",
    "answerText": " Jerusalem"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72074,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of India's Parliamentary Democracy on Trail ?",
    "answerText": " Madhav Godbole"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72075,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Sahitya Manjari (I I parts)”?",
    "answerText": " Vallathol Narayana Menon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72076,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Decline of the West”?",
    "answerText": " O. Spengler"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72077,
    "questionText": " Shik Test is used to diagnose?",
    "answerText": " Diptheria"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72078,
    "questionText": " First Woman Foreign Secretary?",
    "answerText": " Chokila Iyer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72079,
    "questionText": " ചന്ദ്രനിൽ കൂടുതൽ കാണപ്പെടുന്ന ലോഹം? ",
    "answerText": " ടൈറ്റാനിയം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72080,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Roman king who accepted Christianity?",
    "answerText": " Constantine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72081,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of As I See ?",
    "answerText": " Kiran Bcdi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72082,
    "questionText": " Who introduced English Education in Trivandrum?",
    "answerText": " Swathi Thirunal."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72083,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Savithri ?",
    "answerText": " Aurobindo Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72084,
    "questionText": " SmallPox causing virus is ?",
    "answerText": " Variola virus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72085,
    "questionText": " Who is the pro-chancellor of the Universities in Kerala?",
    "answerText": " The Education Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72086,
    "questionText": " Hindustan News Print Factory is located at?",
    "answerText": " Vellur (Kottayam)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72087,
    "questionText": " In which year Kerala State Film Development Corporation (KSFDC) was founded?",
    "answerText": 1975
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72088,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Enigma of Arrival”?",
    "answerText": " V.S.Naipaul"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72089,
    "questionText": " Hottest Place (World)?",
    "answerText": " Azizia (Libya) 58OC"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72090,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of The Da VinciCode ?",
    "answerText": " Dan Brown"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72091,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Rajtarangini”?",
    "answerText": " Kalhana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72092,
    "questionText": " World Population Day is on?",
    "answerText": 44753
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72093,
    "questionText": " Who is the liberator of Venezuela in 1910?",
    "answerText": " Francisco De Miranda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72094,
    "questionText": " Kannur University was founded in?",
    "answerText": 1996
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72095,
    "questionText": " What is the National bird of America?",
    "answerText": " Eagle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72096,
    "questionText": " Second World War became a Global war in?",
    "answerText": 1941
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72097,
    "questionText": " Central Glass and Ceramic Research Station is located at?",
    "answerText": " New Delhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72098,
    "questionText": " Island of Cloves?",
    "answerText": " Zanzibar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72099,
    "questionText": " Mumps causing virus is ?",
    "answerText": " Myxovirus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72100,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Uganda?",
    "answerText": " Kampala"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72101,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Ball Point Pen?",
    "answerText": " John Loud"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72102,
    "questionText": " Who is the creator of the famous characters “Gora; Chitra; Rehman; Mini”",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72103,
    "questionText": " Cromagnan (France) and Grimaldi (ltali) men belonged to which period?",
    "answerText": " Middle Stone Age"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72104,
    "questionText": " In which year American women got voting right?",
    "answerText": 1920
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72105,
    "questionText": " G-15; an economic grouping of developing countries of Asian; African and Latin American countries; was formed in?",
    "answerText": " Malaysia in 1990"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72106,
    "questionText": " Hankow is on the bank of which River?",
    "answerText": " Yangtse-Kiang"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72107,
    "questionText": " The study of microorganisms is called ?",
    "answerText": " Microbiology"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72108,
    "questionText": " The scientific name of Cow is?",
    "answerText": " Bos indica"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72109,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Ellam Chundukal”?",
    "answerText": " G. Sankara Kurup"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72110,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Men from Stone Age to Clone Age ?",
    "answerText": " Bob Beale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72111,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Ashtadhyayi”?",
    "answerText": " Panini"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72112,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of The Perils of Democracy ?",
    "answerText": " P.E. Alexander"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72113,
    "questionText": " The famous writer 'Mali' Madhavan Nair was a champion of which sport?",
    "answerText": " Tennis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72114,
    "questionText": " You are standing in front of The 'Great Banyan Tree'. Where are you now?",
    "answerText": " Indian Botanical Garden Sibpur;Kolkata."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72115,
    "questionText": " Name the ruler who laid the foundation of Cabinet system?",
    "answerText": " Robert Walpole"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72116,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of India for Sale?",
    "answerText": " Chitra Subramaniam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72117,
    "questionText": " Who is the creator of the famous character Hari Pachanan;?",
    "answerText": " C.V.Ramanpilla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72118,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Bermuda Triangle”?",
    "answerText": " Charles Berlitz"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72119,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of ‘My Struggle’?",
    "answerText": " E:K.Nayanar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72120,
    "questionText": " By which treaty The United States of America came to being ?",
    "answerText": " Treaty of Paris in 1783"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72121,
    "questionText": " The Huzur court was reconstructed as?",
    "answerText": " The Raja's Court of Appeal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72122,
    "questionText": " Loneliest Island?",
    "answerText": " Tristan De Gumha (Mid. Atlantic)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72123,
    "questionText": " Thyroid gland is popularly known as ?",
    "answerText": " Adam's Apple."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72124,
    "questionText": " Dublin is on the bank of which River?",
    "answerText": " Liffey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72125,
    "questionText": " Exceptionally more favourable light for stomatal opening is ?",
    "answerText": " Blue"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72126,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Radio Transmitter?",
    "answerText": " Alexanderson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72127,
    "questionText": " Which Travancore king was known as Dharmaraja?",
    "answerText": " Karthika Tirunal Rama Varma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72128,
    "questionText": " Vitamin E is also called?",
    "answerText": " Tocopherol"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72129,
    "questionText": " Who was the French Philosopher who wrote the book ‘Emile’?",
    "answerText": " Rousseau"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72130,
    "questionText": " The vegetation of deserts is called ?",
    "answerText": " Xerophytes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72131,
    "questionText": " Who is the creator of the famous character Anandha Padmanabhan;",
    "answerText": " C.V.Ramanpilla"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72132,
    "questionText": " LAN stands for ?",
    "answerText": " Local Area Network"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72133,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Botswana?",
    "answerText": " Gaborone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72134,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “My Struggle”?",
    "answerText": " EK.Nayanar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72135,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Indira Gandhi: A biography?",
    "answerText": " Pupul Jayakar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72136,
    "questionText": " ADB began its operation in?",
    "answerText": 1966
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72137,
    "questionText": " Which semetic group of people captured Egypt towards BC 1750?",
    "answerText": " Hyksus semetic group"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72138,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Mongolia?",
    "answerText": " Tugrik"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72139,
    "questionText": " ……is writing which the author creates from imagination?",
    "answerText": " Fiction"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72140,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Economic Planning of India Elimination of Child Labour”?",
    "answerText": " Ashok Mehta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72141,
    "questionText": " Tallest Animal?",
    "answerText": " Giraffe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72142,
    "questionText": " Hitler became the Chancellor of Germany on?",
    "answerText": " 30-Jan-33"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72143,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of ‘Crisis into Chaos’?",
    "answerText": " E.M.S. Namboodiripad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72144,
    "questionText": " The dark skinned race of Africa are called ?",
    "answerText": " Negroes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72145,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Brownian Movements?",
    "answerText": " Robert Brown"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72146,
    "questionText": " Sugar metabolism is the function of which hormone?",
    "answerText": " Insulin produced by Pancreas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72147,
    "questionText": " Which is an autonomous bodies established to promote malayalam language and literature?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72148,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Transformer?",
    "answerText": " William Stanley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72149,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “What is the real name of George Eliot”?",
    "answerText": " Mary Ann Evans"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72150,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Andorra?",
    "answerText": " French Franc;"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72151,
    "questionText": " Which is the longest cell of human body?",
    "answerText": " Nerve cell(neuron)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72152,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Antiseptic Surgery?",
    "answerText": " Joseph Lister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72153,
    "questionText": " First Speed Post Centre in Kerala was started at Ernakulam in?",
    "answerText": " Nov-86"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72154,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Lithuania?",
    "answerText": " Vilnius"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72155,
    "questionText": " Who was the first woman Chief Justice of Kerala high court?",
    "answerText": " Sujatha V. Manohar (1994)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72156,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Telegraph Code?",
    "answerText": " Samuel Morse"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72157,
    "questionText": " The study of ageing is known as ?",
    "answerText": " Gerentology"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72158,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Afghanistan?",
    "answerText": " Kabul"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72159,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Which writer is known a Bepoor Sulthan”?",
    "answerText": " Vaikom Muhammed Basheer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72160,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Tungsten?",
    "answerText": " Coolidge"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72161,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Pakistan?",
    "answerText": " Islamabad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72162,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “One World”?",
    "answerText": " Wendell Wilkie"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72163,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The Fury”?",
    "answerText": " Salman Rushdie"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72164,
    "questionText": " New York is on the bank of which River?",
    "answerText": " Hudson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72165,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Without Fear or Favour”?",
    "answerText": " Neelam Sanjeeva Reddy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72166,
    "questionText": " Who introduced travelling courts in Travancore?",
    "answerText": " Velu Tampi Dalawa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72167,
    "questionText": " Confucianism was the new religion founded by?",
    "answerText": " Confucious"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72168,
    "questionText": " The disease characterized by a large amount of water being removed through urine due to the Deficiency of ADH is?",
    "answerText": " Diabetes Insipidus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72169,
    "questionText": " Which King of Travancore made ‘The Pandarapattam Proclamation of 1865’ for agrarian reforms?",
    "answerText": " Ayilyam Thirunal."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72170,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Cinema?",
    "answerText": " Nicolas Lumiere & Edison"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72171,
    "questionText": " ‘Quasi rent’ was popularised by ?",
    "answerText": " Alfred Marshal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72172,
    "questionText": " Herring Pond?",
    "answerText": " Atlantic Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72173,
    "questionText": " Headquarter of IMF is at?",
    "answerText": " Washington; (USA)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72174,
    "questionText": " What is the name of autobiography of Swadeshabhimani Ramakrishnapilla ?",
    "answerText": " Ente Nadukadathal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72175,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “My Days”?",
    "answerText": " R.K. Narayan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72176,
    "questionText": " 239 year old monarchy was abolished in Nepal in?",
    "answerText": 2008
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72177,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Reprieve”?",
    "answerText": " Jean Paul Sartre"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72178,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Waste Land”?",
    "answerText": " T.S.Elliot"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72179,
    "questionText": " Who is known as the 'Father of American Constitution?",
    "answerText": " James Madison"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72180,
    "questionText": " The DNA testng technique was first reported in 1984 by?",
    "answerText": " Sir Alec Jeffreys in England"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72181,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “How to change the world”?",
    "answerText": " Eric Hobsbawm"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72182,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Invitation to the White House”?",
    "answerText": " Hillary Clinton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72183,
    "questionText": " Plants growing on rocks?",
    "answerText": " Lithophytes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72184,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Nineteen Eighty Four”?",
    "answerText": " George Orwell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72185,
    "questionText": " Great Depression striked America in?",
    "answerText": " 1930's"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72186,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Luxembourg?",
    "answerText": " Luxembourg Franc"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72187,
    "questionText": " Who is considered as the father of Politics?",
    "answerText": " Aristotle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72188,
    "questionText": " Who invented the method of smelting iron with coke in 1709?",
    "answerText": " Abraham Derby"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72189,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Simhabhoomi “?",
    "answerText": " S K Pottekadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72190,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Court Dancer; ”?",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72191,
    "questionText": " Who became the first Chairman and first President of the Chinese Republic in 1912?",
    "answerText": " Sun Yat-Sen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72192,
    "questionText": " Which organization introduced HDI in its first Human Development Report published in 1990?",
    "answerText": " United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72193,
    "questionText": " Wembley Stadium (England) is associated with which Sport?",
    "answerText": " Association Football"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72194,
    "questionText": " Who is known as the architect of Soviet Union?",
    "answerText": " Vladimir Lenin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72195,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Elected Chief Minister?",
    "answerText": " EMS Namboothiripad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72196,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Krishnagatha “?",
    "answerText": " Cherusseri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72197,
    "questionText": " Crescograph was invented by ?",
    "answerText": " Jagadish Chandra Bose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72198,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Paradise Lost Paradise· Regained?",
    "answerText": " John Milton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72199,
    "questionText": " Which missionary is the author of MalayalaBhasha?",
    "answerText": " Arch Decon Koshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72200,
    "questionText": " Princess Diana died in a car accident along with Dodi Al Fayed in?",
    "answerText": " Paris"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72201,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of ‘Vrithantha Pathra Pravarthanam’ the first book on journalism in Malayalam?",
    "answerText": " Swadeshabhimani K Ramakrishna Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72202,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Ascent to Everest ?",
    "answerText": " Sir John Hunt"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72203,
    "questionText": " Who is the creator of the famous characters Chirutha; classipper?",
    "answerText": " Thakazhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72204,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Interpreter of Maladies”?",
    "answerText": " Jumpa Lahiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72205,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Zulfi my Friend?",
    "answerText": " Piloo Mody"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72206,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Naked Face ?",
    "answerText": " Sydney Sheldon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72207,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Round Table”?",
    "answerText": " Hazlitt William"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72208,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Fairie Queen?",
    "answerText": " Edmund Spenser"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72209,
    "questionText": " The Renaissance painters painted directly on plaster walls called ?",
    "answerText": " Frescoes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72210,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Kranthadarshikal”?",
    "answerText": " Prof. S. Guptan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72211,
    "questionText": " The smallest ape is?",
    "answerText": " Gibbon."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72212,
    "questionText": " Who has the longest term as the Speaker of Kerala Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " M. Vijayakumar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72213,
    "questionText": " What was the major occupation of the: people in the Sangham Period ?",
    "answerText": " Agriculture"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72214,
    "questionText": " The first and only Cooperative Society of writers, authors and publishers (SPCS), for publishing books and periodicals was set up at Kottayam in?",
    "answerText": 1945
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72215,
    "questionText": " The Union of South Africa became a Republic on?",
    "answerText": " 31st May 1961"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72216,
    "questionText": " In 1954 the US brought most of the South East Asian Countries under a common frame work modelled on NATO called ?",
    "answerText": " SEATO"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72217,
    "questionText": " The Vaccine that is administered to prevent tuberculosis is ?",
    "answerText": " B.C.G (BacillusCalmetteGuerine) vaccine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72218,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Laser?",
    "answerText": " Charles Townes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72219,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Servants of India ?",
    "answerText": " RK Laxman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72220,
    "questionText": " The scientific name of Tapioca is?",
    "answerText": " Manihot Utilissima"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72221,
    "questionText": " Ayyankali was nominated to the Srimulam Prajasabha in?",
    "answerText": 1910
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72222,
    "questionText": " Emma Woodhouse",
    "answerText": " Jane Austen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72223,
    "questionText": " Who is known as 'Payyoli Express'?",
    "answerText": " P T Usha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72224,
    "questionText": " Pazhassi Raja Memorial fame Manathawadi was earlier known as ?",
    "answerText": " Ananthancode."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72225,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Social Contract”?",
    "answerText": " Rousseau"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72226,
    "questionText": " Chinese call Mandarin language as?",
    "answerText": " 'Putoghua' (Common language)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72227,
    "questionText": " … is a copper containing respiratory pigment occurring in arthropods and molluses. It is much less efficient as oxygen carrier?",
    "answerText": " Haemocyanin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72228,
    "questionText": " Archemedes the originator of the law of specific gravity lived in which age ?",
    "answerText": " The Hellenistic Age"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72229,
    "questionText": " Among the chief ministers listed below who did not complete the term of five years?",
    "answerText": " C. Achuthamenon; K. Karunakaran; E.K. Nayanar;A.K Antony D"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72230,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Republic Yugoslavia?",
    "answerText": " Dinar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72231,
    "questionText": " Highest Leaning Tower (World)?",
    "answerText": " Leaning Tower; Pisa (Italy)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72232,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Najma Heptullah?",
    "answerText": " Journey of a Legend"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72233,
    "questionText": " The year in which the first census of Travancore was conducted by Swathi Thirunal is?",
    "answerText": 1836
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72234,
    "questionText": " The year in which Kerala State Film awards were started is?",
    "answerText": 1969
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72235,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Death under Sail ?",
    "answerText": " C.P. Snow"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72236,
    "questionText": " Nivarthana Agitation was in ?",
    "answerText": 1932
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72237,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Electric Motor (DC)?",
    "answerText": " Zenobe Gramme"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72238,
    "questionText": " After the death of Dharmaraja; Who came to the throne of Travancore?",
    "answerText": " Balarama Varma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72239,
    "questionText": " Maginot Line separates?",
    "answerText": " France and Germany."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72240,
    "questionText": " Whis is the Largest trees in plant world ?",
    "answerText": " Conifers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72241,
    "questionText": " The virus which attack bacteria is called?",
    "answerText": " Bacteriophage."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72242,
    "questionText": " Starch is a polymer of ?",
    "answerText": " Hexose Sugar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72243,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of I Follow the Mahatma ?",
    "answerText": " K M Munshi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72244,
    "questionText": " The scientific name of Potato is?",
    "answerText": " Solanum Tuberosum"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72245,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Portrait of a Lady”?",
    "answerText": " Henry James"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72246,
    "questionText": " 'Sarva Siksha Abhiyan' (SSA) launched on?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72247,
    "questionText": " The male sex hormone Testo-sterone is produced by ?",
    "answerText": " Leydig Cells"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72248,
    "questionText": " Sigmond Freud belongs to which country?",
    "answerText": " Austria"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72249,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Man Who Changed China ?",
    "answerText": " Pearl S. Buck"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72250,
    "questionText": " World Tourism Day is observed on?",
    "answerText": 44831
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72251,
    "questionText": " The newspaper Santishtavadi was published in 1867 from?",
    "answerText": " Kottayam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72252,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Georgia?",
    "answerText": " Tbilisi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72253,
    "questionText": " Singing Bird?",
    "answerText": " Nightingale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72254,
    "questionText": " Which king of Travancore followed a policy of' blood and Iron'?",
    "answerText": " Marthandavarma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72255,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Divine Comedy”?",
    "answerText": " A Dante"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72256,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Djibouti?",
    "answerText": " Djibouti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72257,
    "questionText": " ‘Marginal utility theory’ was concepetuallised by?",
    "answerText": " Alfred Marshall"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72258,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Haiti?",
    "answerText": " Port-au-Prince"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72259,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The Hungry Tide. “?",
    "answerText": " Amitav Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72260,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Chief Minister of Kerala?",
    "answerText": " EMS Namboothiripad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72261,
    "questionText": " Who is the founder of the Advaitasrama at Aluva on the banks of Periyar?",
    "answerText": " Sree Narayana Guru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72262,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Onakazhcha”?",
    "answerText": " Lalitham bika Antharjenam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72263,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Fire on the Mountain”?",
    "answerText": " Anita Desai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72264,
    "questionText": " 38th Parallel separates?",
    "answerText": " North and South Korea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72265,
    "questionText": " American Revolution. To protest against the tax on tea; the revolutionaries threw tea boxes from the ship anchored in the Boston Port. This incident is known as ?",
    "answerText": " Boston Tea Party"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72266,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Angles in America”?",
    "answerText": " Tony Kushner"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72267,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Zip Fastener?",
    "answerText": " W.L.Judson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72268,
    "questionText": " In which river Perunthenaruvi waterfalls is located?",
    "answerText": " Pamba river"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72269,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Bifocal lens?",
    "answerText": " Franklin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72270,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Between Hope and History?",
    "answerText": " Bill Clinton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72271,
    "questionText": " Who establishment the Travancore University in 1937?",
    "answerText": " Sri Chithira Thirunal."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72272,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of To Each His Stranger?",
    "answerText": " S H Vatsyayan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72273,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Confidential Clerk”?",
    "answerText": " T.S.Eliot"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72274,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Automobile (magneto)?",
    "answerText": " Daimler"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72275,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Origin of Species ?",
    "answerText": " Charles Darwin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72276,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Naganandan”?",
    "answerText": " King Sri Harsha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72277,
    "questionText": " Who was the Director of Kumarasambavam, the winner of the first Kerala State film award for the best film?",
    "answerText": " A Vincent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72278,
    "questionText": " Who is considered as the 'Father of Atheletic Kerala'?",
    "answerText": " Col Godavarma Raja"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72279,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of The Rogue States?",
    "answerText": " Noam Chomsky"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72280,
    "questionText": " List the Diseases Caused By Bacteria ?",
    "answerText": " Leprosy; Tetanus; Whooping Cough; Typhoid Fever; Cholera; Plague; Tuberculosis; Meningitis; Bacterial Pneumonia; Diarrhoea; Diphtheria; Bacterial dysentry; Anthrax; Syphilis and Gonorrhoea."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72281,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Baliyakala Sakikal”?",
    "answerText": " Vaikom Muhammed Basheer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72282,
    "questionText": " Name the inventeer of Telescope in 1609?",
    "answerText": " Galileo Galilei; an Italian scientist"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72283,
    "questionText": " What are known as suicide bags?",
    "answerText": " Lysosomes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72284,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “War of the Worlds”?",
    "answerText": " The HG Wells"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72285,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The man who killed Gandhi”?",
    "answerText": " Manohar Malgonkar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72286,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Mayilpeeli”?",
    "answerText": " O.N.V Kurup"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72287,
    "questionText": " Kollam Era is also known as ?",
    "answerText": " Malayalam 'Era."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72288,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Inside CBI”?",
    "answerText": " Joginder Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72289,
    "questionText": " First Indian Woman Air-Commodre?",
    "answerText": " Ms.P.Bandhobathyai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72290,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Kerala Governor?",
    "answerText": " B Ramakrishna Rao"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72291,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “VeenaPoovu”?",
    "answerText": " Kumaranasan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72292,
    "questionText": " During which period of evolution man started the settled life?",
    "answerText": " Neolithic period"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72293,
    "questionText": " Sambalpur is on the bank of which River?",
    "answerText": " Mahanadi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72294,
    "questionText": " The Currency of South Africa?",
    "answerText": " Rand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72295,
    "questionText": " Swadeshabhimani Ramakrishnapilla died on?",
    "answerText": " 28 March 1916 at Kannur."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72296,
    "questionText": " Putney is associated with which Sport?",
    "answerText": " Boat-rowing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72297,
    "questionText": " Whis is the Largest flower ?",
    "answerText": " Rafflesia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72298,
    "questionText": " Which is the most populous city with in the world?",
    "answerText": " Shanghai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72299,
    "questionText": " Largest Zoo (India)?",
    "answerText": " Zoological Gardens; Alipur; Calcutta."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72300,
    "questionText": " The Capital of ElSalvador?",
    "answerText": " San Salvador"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72301,
    "questionText": " Kalur International Stadium is now known as?",
    "answerText": " Nehru Stadium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72302,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Welding (Electric)?",
    "answerText": " Thomson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72303,
    "questionText": " Which is the first newspaper published in 1864 from Kochi?",
    "answerText": " ’Paschimataraka’"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72304,
    "questionText": " A poem of fourteen lines is known as?",
    "answerText": " Sonnet"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72305,
    "questionText": " Who led the second expedition of the Portuguese to Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Pedro Alvarez Cabral."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72306,
    "questionText": " Which is the famous Persian religion?",
    "answerText": " Zorastrianism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72307,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Triumph”?",
    "answerText": " John Kenneth Galbraith"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72308,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Living Room?",
    "answerText": " Graham Greene"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72309,
    "questionText": " The highest honor awarded in literature is the Nobel Prize in Literature; awarded since 1901 by?",
    "answerText": " The Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72310,
    "questionText": " First European to visit China?",
    "answerText": " Marco Polo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72311,
    "questionText": " Mussolini was against Socialism and Communism and formed an organisation known as?",
    "answerText": " Fasci di Combattiment"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72312,
    "questionText": " Largest Open University?",
    "answerText": " Indira Gandhi National Open University; New Delhi."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72313,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Man of Destiny ?",
    "answerText": " George Bernard Shaw;"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72314,
    "questionText": " Largest River (India)?",
    "answerText": " The Ganges (6; 679 km)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72315,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “A Pair of Blue Eyes”?",
    "answerText": " Thomas Hardy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72316,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of  Broken Wing?",
    "answerText": " Sarojini Naidu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72317,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The company of women”?",
    "answerText": " Khushwant Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72318,
    "questionText": " Lichenology is the study of ?",
    "answerText": " The study of lichens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72319,
    "questionText": " Uniform Resources Locator (URL) is an electronic address that identifies a?",
    "answerText": " Website."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72320,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Philippines?",
    "answerText": " Manila (Quezon City)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72321,
    "questionText": " The Capital of St. Kitts-Nevis?",
    "answerText": " Basseterre"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72322,
    "questionText": " Pythagoras who made great contributions in Geometry belongs to?",
    "answerText": " Greek"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72323,
    "questionText": " Malaria is caused by ?",
    "answerText": " Plasmodium vivax"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72324,
    "questionText": " The scientific name Pea-cock is ?",
    "answerText": " Pavo cristatus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72325,
    "questionText": " Napolean Bonaparte proclaimed himself the emperor of France in the year?",
    "answerText": 1804
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72326,
    "questionText": " Central Fuel Research Institute is located at?",
    "answerText": " Dhanbad (Bihar)."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72327,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Voice of Conscience?",
    "answerText": " V.V.Giri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72328,
    "questionText": " Who organized Sahodarasangham in 1917?",
    "answerText": " Sahodaran Ayyappan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72329,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Anakaran”?",
    "answerText": " Karoor Neelakanda Pillai"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72330,
    "questionText": " Who was the Chief Minister of Cochin at the time of new state of Travancore - Cochin formed?",
    "answerText": " Ikkanda Warrier."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72331,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Indian struggle”?",
    "answerText": " Subhash Chandra Bose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72332,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “My Life; Law and Other Things”?",
    "answerText": " M C Setal vad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72333,
    "questionText": " PLR stands for?",
    "answerText": " Prime Lending Rate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72334,
    "questionText": " Buddhism reached China from India during the period of?",
    "answerText": " Han dynasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72335,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Beloved”?",
    "answerText": " Toni Morrison"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72336,
    "questionText": " ‘The Republic’ was the famous work of?",
    "answerText": " Plato"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72337,
    "questionText": " The scientific name of Rice is?",
    "answerText": " Oryza Sativa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72338,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Naked Came the Stranger ?",
    "answerText": " Penelope Ashe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72339,
    "questionText": " Thirunavaya-- Famous for Mamangam is in?",
    "answerText": " Malappuram District"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72340,
    "questionText": " Durand Cup is associated with?",
    "answerText": " Football"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72341,
    "questionText": " Surya Nambothiripadu;",
    "answerText": " O. Chandu Menon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72342,
    "questionText": " Which place is known as Kashmir of South India?",
    "answerText": " Munnar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72343,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Oru Deshthinte Katha”?",
    "answerText": " S K Pottekadu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72344,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “All the Prime Minister's Men”?",
    "answerText": " . Janardhan Thakur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72345,
    "questionText": " K T D C was formed in?",
    "answerText": 1966
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72346,
    "questionText": " SQL stands for?",
    "answerText": " Structured Query Language"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72347,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The Vendor of sweets”?",
    "answerText": " R.K. Narayan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72348,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Locomotive?",
    "answerText": " Richard Travithick"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72349,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “My Music; My Life”?",
    "answerText": " Ravi Shankar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72350,
    "questionText": " ….is the sustained rise in prices caused by an increase in the supply of money?",
    "answerText": " Inflation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72351,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Martyr”?",
    "answerText": " Kuldip Nayar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72352,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Freedom in Exile ?",
    "answerText": " Dalai Lama"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72353,
    "questionText": " Which was a white terrorist gang working in America during the period of Great Depression ?",
    "answerText": " Ku Klux Klan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72354,
    "questionText": " The Sabarigiri Hydroelectric project is situated which river?",
    "answerText": " Pamba"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72355,
    "questionText": " The century from 1750 to 1850 is also known as ?",
    "answerText": " The 'Age of Revolutions'"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72356,
    "questionText": " Which civilization is considered to be the world's first urban civilisation ?",
    "answerText": " Mesopotamian civilization"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72357,
    "questionText": " Who is known as the founder of Early Babilonian Empire?",
    "answerText": " Hammurabi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72358,
    "questionText": " America was named after the Portuguese sailor ?",
    "answerText": " Amerigo Vespucci"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72359,
    "questionText": " The hanging gardens of Babilona was built in the name of?",
    "answerText": " Nebuchandnessar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72360,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Wings of Fire ?",
    "answerText": " A.PJ. Abdul Kalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72361,
    "questionText": " In which year British merchants exported pepper to England for the first time from Cochin ?",
    "answerText": 1626
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72362,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The Shadow Lines”?",
    "answerText": " Amitav Ghosh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72363,
    "questionText": " Who invented Antiseptic Surgery (1867)",
    "answerText": " Joseph Listor"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72364,
    "questionText": " The World Trade Organisation (WTO); was established on?",
    "answerText": " 1-Jan-95"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72365,
    "questionText": " Bombay Gold Cup is associated with?",
    "answerText": " Hockey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72366,
    "questionText": " Kathakali is the developed form of?",
    "answerText": " Krishnanattam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72367,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Book of Unforgettable Women”?",
    "answerText": " Khushwant Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72368,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Netherlands?",
    "answerText": " Guilder"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72369,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Inside Europe ?",
    "answerText": " John-Gunther"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72370,
    "questionText": " Who is the creator of the famous character Gulliver?",
    "answerText": " Jonathan Swift"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72371,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Argentina?",
    "answerText": " Peso"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72372,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ The Golden Gate”?",
    "answerText": " Vikram Seth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72373,
    "questionText": " Largest Library (World)?",
    "answerText": " United States Library of Congress (Washington) The Lenin State Library Moscow- Russia)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72374,
    "questionText": " Those who believe in the life; death and resurrection of Jesus Christ came to be known as ?",
    "answerText": " Christians"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72375,
    "questionText": " Only South East Asian country never occupied by any European powers?",
    "answerText": " Thailand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72376,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Sacred Games?",
    "answerText": " Vikram Chandra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72377,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Smarakashilakal “?",
    "answerText": " Punathil KunjabdulJah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72378,
    "questionText": " Who was the Lady IPS Officer from Kerala?",
    "answerText": " Sreelekha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72379,
    "questionText": " Silent Valley National Park was set up in 1984 at?",
    "answerText": " Mannarkad in Palakkad district"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72380,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Rainbow”?",
    "answerText": " Pearl S. Buck"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72381,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Half a Life”?",
    "answerText": " V.S.Naipaul"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72382,
    "questionText": " Which is the most intelligent ape?",
    "answerText": " Chimpanzee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72383,
    "questionText": " Which is the Malayalam feature film in which famous football player I M Vijayan acted as hero?",
    "answerText": " 'Santham'"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72384,
    "questionText": " Anchal stamps of Travancore existed till?",
    "answerText": 1952
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72385,
    "questionText": " Vitamin D is also called?",
    "answerText": " Calciferol"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72386,
    "questionText": " Highest Gateway (India)?",
    "answerText": " Buland Darwaza"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72387,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Speaker of Kerala Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " R. Sankara Narayana Thampi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72388,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “A Voice of Freedom”?",
    "answerText": " Nayantara Sahgal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72389,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Albania?",
    "answerText": " Tirana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72390,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Tunisia?",
    "answerText": " Dinar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72391,
    "questionText": " Highest venoumous snake is ?",
    "answerText": " King Kobra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72392,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Memories of the Rationalist ?",
    "answerText": " Vasanth Sathe"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72393,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Myanmar (Burma)?",
    "answerText": " Kyat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72394,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “The Vendor of sweets”?",
    "answerText": " R.K. Narayan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72395,
    "questionText": " To end the First World War an armistice (Peace Agreement) was signed on ?",
    "answerText": " November 11;1918"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72396,
    "questionText": " The economic condition in which the rate at which the general level of prices for goods and services is rising and subsequently; purchasing power is falling is called?",
    "answerText": " Inflation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72397,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Refrigerator?",
    "answerText": " Harrison & Catlin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72398,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Tholkappiya Poonga”?",
    "answerText": " M. Karunanidhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72399,
    "questionText": " Who is the creator of the famous characters iago; Macbeth; Jessica?",
    "answerText": " Shakespeare"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72400,
    "questionText": " Kerala Kalamandalam at present is situated in?",
    "answerText": " Vallathol Nagar in Thrissur district"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72401,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Liberia?",
    "answerText": " Liberian Dollar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72402,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Age of Reason?",
    "answerText": " Jean-Paul Sartre"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72403,
    "questionText": " The year in which Doordarshan started telecasting in Malayalam is?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72404,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “India 2020”?",
    "answerText": " A.P.J. Abdul Kalam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72405,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Morocco?",
    "answerText": " Rabat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72406,
    "questionText": " World Literacy Day is on?",
    "answerText": 44812
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72407,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Lipika ?",
    "answerText": " Rabindranath Tagore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72408,
    "questionText": " Plant genetics is the study of ?",
    "answerText": " Genetic inheritance in plants"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72409,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Curtain Raisers ?",
    "answerText": " Natwar Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72410,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “ Jnanappana”?",
    "answerText": " Poonthanam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72411,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Identity and Violence?",
    "answerText": " Prof.Amartya Sen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72412,
    "questionText": " Name the American President who chose the site for White House?",
    "answerText": " Herbert Hover"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72413,
    "questionText": " Dengu fever; also called Breakbone fever; is transmitted mainly through?",
    "answerText": " Aedes Aegypti Mosquitoes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72414,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Darkness Visible?",
    "answerText": " William Styron"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72415,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of In Memmorium?",
    "answerText": " Alfred Tennyson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72416,
    "questionText": " The popular ministry of Travancore- Cochin was headed by ?",
    "answerText": " T.K. Narayana Pillai; the Chief Minister of Travancore at the time of integration."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72417,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Prem Pachisi”?",
    "answerText": " Munshi Prem Chand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72418,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the famous book' Historia Naturalis'?",
    "answerText": " Pliny"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72419,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Niger?",
    "answerText": " Niamey"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72420,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Interpretation of Dreams’”?",
    "answerText": " Sigmond Freud"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72421,
    "questionText": " Mecca of Kerala is?",
    "answerText": " Ponnani (Malappuram)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72422,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of The Vicar of Wakefield ?",
    "answerText": " Oliver Goldsmith"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72423,
    "questionText": " Normal count level of WBC in Blood ?",
    "answerText": " 5;000 to 9;000 ccg Blood"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72424,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Cherry Orchard?",
    "answerText": " Anton Chekov"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72425,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Lord Jim?",
    "answerText": " Joseph Conrad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72426,
    "questionText": " Which missionary is the author of Puthanpana Chaturasyam?",
    "answerText": " Amosu Pathiri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72427,
    "questionText": " India's national flower ?",
    "answerText": " Lotus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72428,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Angels and Demons”?",
    "answerText": " George Orwell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72429,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Between Hope and History”?",
    "answerText": " Bill Clinton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72430,
    "questionText": " CENTO stands for?",
    "answerText": " Central Treaty Oganisation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72431,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Barbados?",
    "answerText": " Dollar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72432,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Bride's Book of Beauty ?",
    "answerText": " Mulk Raj Anand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72433,
    "questionText": " Which newspaper is known as the voice of the Muslim League?",
    "answerText": " Chandrika"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72434,
    "questionText": " Madrid is on the bank of which River?",
    "answerText": " Manzaneres"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72435,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Hong Kong?",
    "answerText": " Hong Kong Dollar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72436,
    "questionText": " Sumerian civilisation flourished on the banks of which rivers?",
    "answerText": " Euphrates and Tigris"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72437,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Anandrnath”?",
    "answerText": " Bankim Chandra Chatterjee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72438,
    "questionText": " Earliest available inscription dated in the Kollam Era; the Mampalli Plate (149) is ascribed to?",
    "answerText": " Sri Vallabalan Kotha of Venadu."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72439,
    "questionText": " Who is considered as the father of the Science of Reasoning?",
    "answerText": " Aristotle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72440,
    "questionText": " Who is known as 'Golden Girl'?",
    "answerText": " P T Usha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72441,
    "questionText": " First President of Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": " W.C.Bonerjee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72442,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Bread”?",
    "answerText": " K.A.Abbas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72443,
    "questionText": " The International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD) or World Bank was established in?",
    "answerText": 1944
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72444,
    "questionText": " The Capital of Suriname?",
    "answerText": " Paramaribo"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72445,
    "questionText": " Which cit y is known as “City of Seven Hills?",
    "answerText": " Rome"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72446,
    "questionText": " Which dynasty established China's first strong central government?",
    "answerText": " The Qin dynasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72447,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Baburnama ?",
    "answerText": " Babur (Translated into English by John Falkland)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72448,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “White House Years”?",
    "answerText": " Henry Kissinger"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72449,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Kore Kagaz”?",
    "answerText": " Amrita Pritam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72450,
    "questionText": " George Washington became the President of America in the year?",
    "answerText": 1789
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72451,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of “Trinity”?",
    "answerText": " Leon Uris"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72452,
    "questionText": " What is the tenure of Kerala Legislative Assembly?",
    "answerText": " Five years "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72453,
    "questionText": " First woman to walk in space (Russia)?",
    "answerText": " Svetlana Savitskaya space"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72454,
    "questionText": " Nila is the old name of which river?",
    "answerText": " Bharathappuzha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72455,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Rubber (vulcanised)?",
    "answerText": " Goodyear"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72456,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Sesame and Lilies J?",
    "answerText": " ohn Ruskin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72457,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Family Reunion ?",
    "answerText": " TSEliot"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72458,
    "questionText": " The organ without muscle is ?",
    "answerText": " Lungs"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72459,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of Leaves of Grass ?",
    "answerText": " Walt Whitman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72460,
    "questionText": " First Indian to become President of International Court of Justice?",
    "answerText": " Dr. Nagendra Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72461,
    "questionText": " Which is the world's longest artificially created water way ?",
    "answerText": " The Grand Canal (extends more than 1600 Kilometers from Hangzhou in the south to Beijing in the north)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72462,
    "questionText": " The first English School was opened at TVM in 1834 by?",
    "answerText": " Swathi Thirunal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72463,
    "questionText": " Who is the inventor of Balloon?",
    "answerText": " Montgolfier"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72464,
    "questionText": " Chickengunya a viral disease is caused by ?",
    "answerText": " Aedes Aegypti."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72465,
    "questionText": " Trojan horse tactics was the policy adopted during the Second World War by?",
    "answerText": " Germany"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72466,
    "questionText": " Operation Enduring Freedom aimed at disbanding al-Qaeda bases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72467,
    "questionText": " The Currency of Emirates Republic?"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72468,
    "questionText": " Which mountain range stretches from Gujarat in west to Delhi in the north?",
    "answerText": " Aravallis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72469,
    "questionText": " What is the name of the highest summit of Nilgiri Hills?",
    "answerText": " Doda-betta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72470,
    "questionText": " ഭൂവൽക്കത്തിൽ സുലഭമായ ലോഹം? ",
    "answerText": " അലൂമിനിയം "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72471,
    "questionText": " For whose removal Parliament’s resolution is not needed?",
    "answerText": " Judge of Supreme Court"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72472,
    "questionText": " In which animal skin is a respiratory organ?",
    "answerText": " Frog"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72473,
    "questionText": " What is the largest state in the USA?",
    "answerText": " Alaska"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72474,
    "questionText": " Which crop does India have the largest cultivated area in the world?",
    "answerText": " Rice"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72475,
    "questionText": " St. Thomas came to India in 1st century A. D. to propogate christianity. During which reign did he come?",
    "answerText": " Gondophernes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72476,
    "questionText": " What do the contact of two air masses differing sharply in humidity originate?",
    "answerText": " Temperate cyclones"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72477,
    "questionText": " Which is the birth place of Guru Gobind Singh?",
    "answerText": " Patna"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72478,
    "questionText": " In which country are ‘Dykes’ especially constructed?",
    "answerText": " Norway"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72479,
    "questionText": " Which formulates fiscal policy?",
    "answerText": " Finance Ministry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72480,
    "questionText": " Who was the first black tennis player to win a Wombledon title?",
    "answerText": " Althea Gibson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72481,
    "questionText": " Of which metals were the tools and weapons of Harappan civilisation?",
    "answerText": " Copper; tin and bronze"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72482,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest sea in the world?",
    "answerText": " South China Sea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72483,
    "questionText": " What does the theory of Fundamental Rights imply?",
    "answerText": " Limited government"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72484,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Chairman of the Planning Commission?",
    "answerText": " Pt. Jawahar Lal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72485,
    "questionText": " Which polymeric material is used for making bullet proof jacket?",
    "answerText": " KEVLAR"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72486,
    "questionText": " By whom was ltmad-ud-daula’s tomb at Agra was built?",
    "answerText": " Nur Jahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72487,
    "questionText": " The cauliflower shape is associated with which cloud formations?",
    "answerText": " Cumulus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72488,
    "questionText": " Which organs are morphologically different but perform the same function?",
    "answerText": " Analogous organs"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72489,
    "questionText": " The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty came into force in which year?",
    "answerText": 1970
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72490,
    "questionText": " What is used in preparing match sticks?",
    "answerText": " Red phosphorus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72491,
    "questionText": " Nobel Prize winning scientist James D. Watson is known for his work in which area?",
    "answerText": " Genetics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72492,
    "questionText": " Knowledge about the- existence of which animal is doubtful in the Indus VaElley Civilization?",
    "answerText": " Cat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72493,
    "questionText": " Which is present in the largest amount in terms of percent by mass in the earth’s crust?",
    "answerText": " Oxygen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72494,
    "questionText": " In which year was the first International Film Festival of India held?",
    "answerText": " 1952 at Bombay"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72495,
    "questionText": " Baan Ki-moon; the former UNO Secretary-General belong to which country?",
    "answerText": " South Korea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72496,
    "questionText": " Where are a large number of species are found within a small unit of area?",
    "answerText": " Wet evergreen equatorial forests"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72497,
    "questionText": " In which plan was the growth rate of agricultural production negative?",
    "answerText": " Third Plan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72498,
    "questionText": " Who was not the member of the Cabinet Mission which visited India in 1946?",
    "answerText": " Lord Mountbatten"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72499,
    "questionText": " Which was the Princely State which acceeded to the Indian Union after a plebiscite?",
    "answerText": " Junagadh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72500,
    "questionText": " Galvanised iron sheets have a coating of which metal?",
    "answerText": " Zinc"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72501,
    "questionText": " Palaeobotany is the branch of botany; what do we study about in this branch?",
    "answerText": " Plant fossils"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72502,
    "questionText": " What is the time required by moonlight to reach the earth?",
    "answerText": " 1.3 sec"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72503,
    "questionText": " Who wrote Sanskrit Grammar?",
    "answerText": " Panini"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72504,
    "questionText": " Which Mahajanapada was situated on the bank of river Godawari?",
    "answerText": " Assaka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72505,
    "questionText": " Journalist’s day was celebrated for the first time all over the country on which date?",
    "answerText": " Oct 1; 1984"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72506,
    "questionText": " “The Vedas contain all the truth” was interpreted by which person?",
    "answerText": " Swami Dayanand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72507,
    "questionText": " Which state in India has the largest area under forests?",
    "answerText": " Madhya Pradesh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72508,
    "questionText": " What is the major source of oceanic salinity?",
    "answerText": " Rivers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72509,
    "questionText": " Which property of the elements is a whole number?",
    "answerText": " Atomic number"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72510,
    "questionText": " At present the Rajya Sabha consists of how many members?",
    "answerText": 245
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72511,
    "questionText": " Which waterfall in India has the most height?",
    "answerText": " Kunchikal Falls"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72512,
    "questionText": " Between which dates there is a continual daylight or summer in the Arctic regions?",
    "answerText": " 21st March to 23rd September"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72513,
    "questionText": " Which Directive Principle of State Policy has NOT been implemented so far?",
    "answerText": " Uniform civil code for the citizens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72514,
    "questionText": " Who is the first non-Indian to receive the Bharat Ratna?",
    "answerText": " Khan Abdul Ghaffar Khan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72515,
    "questionText": " The word “biodiversity” is a combination of which two words?",
    "answerText": " Biology and diversity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72516,
    "questionText": " Hyder Ali was defeated at porto Novo by which British General?",
    "answerText": " Sir Eyrecoot"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72517,
    "questionText": " Who was the largest serving Chief Minister in India?",
    "answerText": " Jyoti Basu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72518,
    "questionText": " Aravalli ranges are an example of which mountains?",
    "answerText": " Residual mountains"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72519,
    "questionText": " Who is the author of the book ‘My Country; My Life’?",
    "answerText": " L.K. Advani"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72520,
    "questionText": " Economic Planning is a subject of which list?",
    "answerText": " Union List"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72521,
    "questionText": " In respect of which states has Union Parliament power to legislate on the subjects of all three lists?",
    "answerText": " Union Territories"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72522,
    "questionText": " In the Interim Government formed in the year 1946; who held the portfolio of Defence?",
    "answerText": " Baldev Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72523,
    "questionText": " Who was the Finance Minister of India in the Interim Government during 1946-1947?",
    "answerText": " R. K. Shanmukham Chetty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72524,
    "questionText": " Which is the basis of modern periodic table?",
    "answerText": " Atomic number"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72525,
    "questionText": " Which is the major silk producing state in India?",
    "answerText": " Karnataka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72526,
    "questionText": " Which is similar to the Taj Mahal in construction?",
    "answerText": " Humayun’s tomb"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72527,
    "questionText": " When is International Day for Tolerance; recognized– the UN is observed?",
    "answerText": " 16-Nov-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72528,
    "questionText": " Why is tetracycline is used?",
    "answerText": " As anti-plague drug"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72529,
    "questionText": " Which of appointment is not made by the President of India?",
    "answerText": " Speaker of the Lok Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72530,
    "questionText": " How are the Himalayan rivers?",
    "answerText": " Snow fed"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72531,
    "questionText": " On which date was Mahatma Gandhi assassinated?",
    "answerText": " January 30; 1948"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72532,
    "questionText": " What is the role of in the rabbit and horse; the appendix?",
    "answerText": " It helps in digestion of cellulose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72533,
    "questionText": " By whom was the temple of Konark built?",
    "answerText": " Narsimha of the Eastern Ganges"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72534,
    "questionText": " Which chamber of human heart pumps fully oxy; genated blood to aorta and hence to the body?",
    "answerText": " Left Ventricle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72535,
    "questionText": " Who is competent to prescribe conditions as for acquiring Indian citizenship?",
    "answerText": " Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72536,
    "questionText": " Which polymer is widely used for making bullet proof material?",
    "answerText": " Polyethylene"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72537,
    "questionText": " Which President of-India served for two terms?",
    "answerText": " Rajendra Prasad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72538,
    "questionText": " The first Muslim conquest of the Hindu Kingdoms of Deccan was effected by whose forces?",
    "answerText": " Alauddin Khilji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72539,
    "questionText": " Which animal was known to ancient Vedic people?",
    "answerText": " Lion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72540,
    "questionText": " Which sets of cities is located on the reference longitude for Indian standard time?",
    "answerText": " Kakinanda-Pondicherry"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72541,
    "questionText": " Charles Correa has distinguished himself in which field?",
    "answerText": " Architecture"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72542,
    "questionText": " Who is known as the Ught of Asia?",
    "answerText": " Lord Buddha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72543,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of Food and Agriculture Organisation?",
    "answerText": " Rome"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72544,
    "questionText": " Who was the Mughal Emperor to have lifted the Jaziya on Hindus?",
    "answerText": " Akbar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72545,
    "questionText": " What does the outermost whorl of Bougainvillea flower consist of?",
    "answerText": " Bract"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72546,
    "questionText": " Energy transferred to a person through gamma rays is measured in by which unit?",
    "answerText": " Roentgens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72547,
    "questionText": " To a space traveller on moon; how does the lunar sky during day time appear?",
    "answerText": " Black"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72548,
    "questionText": " In which process the internal energy of a system remains constant?",
    "answerText": " Isothermal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72549,
    "questionText": " Where are Tapovan and Vishnugarh Hydroelectric Projects located?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72550,
    "questionText": " Mercury is transported in metal containers made of which metal?",
    "answerText": " Iron"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72551,
    "questionText": " The President of the Indian Union has the same constitutional authority as which country?",
    "answerText": " British Monarch"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72552,
    "questionText": " Rajiv Gandhi National Flying Institute is has been established in which State?",
    "answerText": " Maharashtra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72553,
    "questionText": " Which is the God who is the most prominent in ‘Rigaveda’?",
    "answerText": " Indra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72554,
    "questionText": " With which can Radio wave of constant amplitude be generated?",
    "answerText": " Oscillator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72555,
    "questionText": " What is the growth movement in plant due to light called?",
    "answerText": " Phototropism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72556,
    "questionText": " Feroz Gandhi Award; is given for outstanding performance in which field?",
    "answerText": " Journalism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72557,
    "questionText": " Who was first President of U.S.A. to visit India?",
    "answerText": " D. W. Eisenhower"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72558,
    "questionText": " Which was the Sultan who called himself Naib-i-Khudai or Deputy of the God;?",
    "answerText": " Balban"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72559,
    "questionText": " Which Indian epic was filmed by British Director Peter Brook?",
    "answerText": " Mahabharat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72560,
    "questionText": " Of which purpose was Nationalisation of banks done?",
    "answerText": " Consolidating the economy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72561,
    "questionText": " Which National Highways of India is the longest?",
    "answerText": " NH 7"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72562,
    "questionText": " During which Gupta king’s reign did the chinese traveller Fahien visit India?",
    "answerText": " Chandragupta II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72563,
    "questionText": " Which antimicrobial drug is suitable for treatment of both tuberculosis and leprosy?",
    "answerText": " Rifampicin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72564,
    "questionText": " For which snake is the diet mainly composed of their snakes?",
    "answerText": " Kinqcobra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72565,
    "questionText": " The United Nations declared 2010 as which International Year?",
    "answerText": " Seafarer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72566,
    "questionText": " The mass-energy relation is the outcome of which theory?",
    "answerText": " Special theory of relativity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72567,
    "questionText": " Who deserves the credit for contruction of Lal Quila?",
    "answerText": " Shahjahan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72568,
    "questionText": " Which rulers held a religious assembly at Prayag every five years?",
    "answerText": " Harshavardhana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72569,
    "questionText": " By whom was the Indian Independence League set up?",
    "answerText": " Ras Behari Bose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72570,
    "questionText": " Regatta is associated with which sports event?",
    "answerText": " Rowing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72571,
    "questionText": " Kamlesh Mehta has distinguished hems elf in which game/sport?",
    "answerText": " Table Tennis"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72572,
    "questionText": " Which colour of heat radiation represents the highest temperature?",
    "answerText": " White"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72573,
    "questionText": " Who founded the French School of Regional Geography?",
    "answerText": " Paul Vidal de in Blache"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72574,
    "questionText": " Mirage is observed in a desert due to the phenomenon of which reflection?",
    "answerText": " Total reflection"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72575,
    "questionText": " In which year was the first no confidence motion moved in the Lok Sabha after independence?",
    "answerText": 1963
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72576,
    "questionText": " Thanatology is the study of what?",
    "answerText": " Death"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72577,
    "questionText": " The first neutron reactor of India; ‘Kamini’; is situated at which place?",
    "answerText": " Kalpakkam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72578,
    "questionText": " Which crop enrich the soil with nitrogen?",
    "answerText": " Pea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72579,
    "questionText": " Which Sultan founded a town where now stands Agra?",
    "answerText": " Sikandar Lodi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72580,
    "questionText": " Soil can best be conserved on the hills by which of the cultivating methods?",
    "answerText": " Contour ploughing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72581,
    "questionText": " Where does rainfall from the south-west monsoon reach?",
    "answerText": " Delta region of Mahanadi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72582,
    "questionText": " In which organ of the human body are the lymphocyte cells formed?",
    "answerText": " Spleen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72583,
    "questionText": " Who was the first PM of England?",
    "answerText": " Gladstone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72584,
    "questionText": " Where are the islands of Seychelles located?",
    "answerText": " Indian Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72585,
    "questionText": " In India; in which was the service tax first introduced?",
    "answerText": 1994
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72586,
    "questionText": " What is the title of A.P.J. Abdul Kalam’s autobiography?",
    "answerText": " Wings of Fire"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72587,
    "questionText": " During which Plan did prices show a decline?",
    "answerText": " First"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72588,
    "questionText": " The tendency of liquid drop to contract and why does it occupy minimum area?",
    "answerText": " Due to Surface tension"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72589,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of Oil and National Gas Commission?",
    "answerText": " Dehradun"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72590,
    "questionText": " Which is the example of crater lake?",
    "answerText": " Oregon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72591,
    "questionText": " Why are the movements of leaves of the sensitive plant Mimosa pundica?",
    "answerText": " Due to Seismonasty"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72592,
    "questionText": " What is the slow wobbling of Earth as it spins on its axis called?",
    "answerText": " Precession"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72593,
    "questionText": " Which form an irreversible complex With haemoglobin of blood?",
    "answerText": " Carbon monoxide"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72594,
    "questionText": " Which crop are grown mainly in the irrigated areas during Zaid?",
    "answerText": " Moong and Urad"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72595,
    "questionText": " Primitive people practice animal rearing in the tropical grasslands of which area?",
    "answerText": " East Africa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72596,
    "questionText": " Kodaikanal; the famous hill-station of South India; is situated on which hills?",
    "answerText": " Palni hills"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72597,
    "questionText": " Why can Insects move on the surface of water without sinking?",
    "answerText": " Due to Surface tension of water"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72598,
    "questionText": " Neap tides occur during which phase of the moon?",
    "answerText": " First and third quarter"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72599,
    "questionText": " Which type of forest exhibits highest bio-diversity?",
    "answerText": " Tropical rain forest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72600,
    "questionText": " Indian Standard Meridian’ passes through which states?",
    "answerText": " UP; MP Orissa and AP"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72601,
    "questionText": " Who won the Hockey Gold (men) in the 1992 Barcelona Games?",
    "answerText": " Germany"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72602,
    "questionText": " Which tissue is responsible for the secondary growth?",
    "answerText": " Cambium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72603,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of the Nanda dynasty?",
    "answerText": " Mahapadma Nanda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72604,
    "questionText": " By what name is the Ganga known in Bangladesh?",
    "answerText": " Padma"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72605,
    "questionText": " The first Commonwealth Games were held in 1930 Which country hosted the games?",
    "answerText": " Canada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72606,
    "questionText": " In which year was Vande Mataram first sung at the session of the Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": 1896
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72607,
    "questionText": " Which local wind is not characteristically hot and dry?",
    "answerText": " Mistral"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72608,
    "questionText": " Why are the Fundamental Freedoms under Article 19 suspended during emergency?",
    "answerText": " War or external aggression"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72609,
    "questionText": " How many Regional Commissions are established by the UN Economic and Social Council?",
    "answerText": 5
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72610,
    "questionText": " Jaspal Rana is a distinguished athlete in which game?",
    "answerText": " Shooting"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72611,
    "questionText": " In which year was the Indus Valley Civilisation discovered?",
    "answerText": 1921
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72612,
    "questionText": " Machael Ferrrera is associated with which game?",
    "answerText": " Snooker"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72613,
    "questionText": " To which group do the tribals of central and southern India belong?",
    "answerText": " Proto-Australoids"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72614,
    "questionText": " Which decade is celebrated as decade of Action for road safety?",
    "answerText": " 2011-2020"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72615,
    "questionText": " Which region has internal drainage?",
    "answerText": " Rajasthan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72616,
    "questionText": " What is the major ingredient of leather?",
    "answerText": " Collagen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72617,
    "questionText": " Who was the founder of the second Afghan Empire in India?",
    "answerText": " Sher Shah Suri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72618,
    "questionText": " During the Sangam Age; Uraiyur was the capital of which ruler?",
    "answerText": " Cholas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72619,
    "questionText": " Indian Army’s School of Artillery is located at which place?",
    "answerText": " Deolali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72620,
    "questionText": " 97% of the atmosphere lies within how many kilometers of the surface of the earth?",
    "answerText": " 5 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72621,
    "questionText": " On the death of Gandhiji; who said that “The light has gone out of our lives…..”?",
    "answerText": " Jawaharlal Nehru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72622,
    "questionText": " Which religion was patronised by Rashtrakutas?",
    "answerText": " Jainism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72623,
    "questionText": " From which sector is the largest contribution in India’s National Income?",
    "answerText": " Tertiary sector"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72624,
    "questionText": " Who were the first Europeans to set up sea trade centers in India?",
    "answerText": " The Portuguese"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72625,
    "questionText": " Rupee was devalued by what percent in July 1991?",
    "answerText": " 20 Percent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72626,
    "questionText": " In our houses we get 220 V A. C What does the value 220 represent?",
    "answerText": " Effective voltage"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72627,
    "questionText": " Which rural bank has been named after a river?",
    "answerText": " Varada Grameen Bank"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72628,
    "questionText": " Which is an insectivorous plant?",
    "answerText": " Nepenthes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72629,
    "questionText": " First Telephone line was started between Kolkata and Diamond Harbour?",
    "answerText": 1851
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72630,
    "questionText": " When Abdur Razzak from Persia visited Hampi; who was the ruler of Vijayanagar in South India?",
    "answerText": " Devaraya II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72631,
    "questionText": " Which States has granted Sanskrit language the status of the second official language of the State?",
    "answerText": " Uttarakhand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72632,
    "questionText": " Which sector is the largest emitter of greenhouse gases in India?",
    "answerText": " Electric power generation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72633,
    "questionText": " Which naturally occurring element in the rice husk makes it termite resistant?",
    "answerText": " Silicon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72634,
    "questionText": " When it is 12:00 noon in India; what would be the time in San Francisco (USA)?",
    "answerText": " 8 : 30 p.m. of previous day"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72635,
    "questionText": " In whose court was a Chinese embassy sent by Tang emperor?",
    "answerText": " Harshavardhana"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72636,
    "questionText": " To which duties is the system of value added taxation applicable?",
    "answerText": " Excise duties"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72637,
    "questionText": " Which state is with the largest area under waste land?",
    "answerText": " Jammu and Kashmir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72638,
    "questionText": " Aretes are sharp ridges which develop between adjacent?",
    "answerText": " Cirques"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72639,
    "questionText": " Who was the first woman minister of a state?",
    "answerText": " Rajkumari Amrit Kaur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72640,
    "questionText": " Which phenomena can not be attributed to the refraction of light?",
    "answerText": " Redshift"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72641,
    "questionText": " Who sings on One-rupee currency notes?",
    "answerText": " Finance Secretary of India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72642,
    "questionText": " Which Ashokan inscription gives an account of the Kalinga war and its effects?",
    "answerText": " Minor Rock Edict XIII"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72643,
    "questionText": " Meghnad Saha is known for his contribution in which field?",
    "answerText": " Physics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72644,
    "questionText": " Which oil fields of India is the oldest and still producing oil?",
    "answerText": " Digboi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72645,
    "questionText": " Which was the capital of the kingdom of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    "answerText": " Lahore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72646,
    "questionText": " Michael Ferreira is associated with which game/sport?",
    "answerText": " Billiards"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72647,
    "questionText": " In which vally is the Himalayan pass Shipki La located?",
    "answerText": " Sutlej valley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72648,
    "questionText": " Which writ is a bulwark of personal freedom?",
    "answerText": " Habeas Corpus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72649,
    "questionText": " The United Nations declared 2013 as the International Year of which coperation?",
    "answerText": " Water Cooperation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72650,
    "questionText": " During the Mughal rule; by which name was the copper coin known?",
    "answerText": " Dam"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72651,
    "questionText": " Which Public Sector bank’ emblem figures a dog and the words ‘faithful; friendly’ in it?",
    "answerText": " Syndicate Bank"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72652,
    "questionText": " Buddha and Mahavira died during which reign?",
    "answerText": " Ajatashatru"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72653,
    "questionText": " Fluorescent tubes are fitted with a choke. What does the choke coil?",
    "answerText": " Reduces current in the circuit"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72654,
    "questionText": " Which natural region is best known for the production of grapes?",
    "answerText": " Mediterranean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72655,
    "questionText": " Why are Clear nights cooler than cloudy nights?",
    "answerText": " Because of radiation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72656,
    "questionText": " What is a glass sided tank; bowl in which aquatic animals live?",
    "answerText": " Aquarium"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72657,
    "questionText": " Which structure was constructed by Emperor Akbar in Fatehpur Sikri?",
    "answerText": " Panch Mahal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72658,
    "questionText": " On which bank is Hampi is situated?",
    "answerText": " Tungabhadra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72659,
    "questionText": " Where is the headquarters of International Olympic Committee?",
    "answerText": " At Lausanne (Switzerland)"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72660,
    "questionText": " Who was the first monarch of Magadh kingdom In the sixth century B.C.?",
    "answerText": " Bimbisara"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72661,
    "questionText": " Which works is ascribed to the famous poet Rajasekhara?",
    "answerText": " Karpurmanjari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72662,
    "questionText": " The year 1995 is the golden Jubilee year of which international organisations?",
    "answerText": " UNO"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72663,
    "questionText": " Which is poorest state in India?",
    "answerText": " Orissa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72664,
    "questionText": " The source of India’s sovereignty lies in which thing?",
    "answerText": " Preamble to the Constitution"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72665,
    "questionText": " Who has scored the slowest century in the test cricket?",
    "answerText": " Mudassar Nazar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72666,
    "questionText": " In which latitudes largest quantities of bauxite is found?",
    "answerText": " Tropical latitudes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72667,
    "questionText": " The Karakoram Highway connects which pairs of countries?",
    "answerText": " China-Pakistan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72668,
    "questionText": " Which Gupta ruler was related to the Licchavis on his mother's side?",
    "answerText": " Samudragupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72669,
    "questionText": " Which helped to develop close ties between the government and the masses?",
    "answerText": " Ryotwari Settlement"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72670,
    "questionText": " Where is the average annual rainfall highest?",
    "answerText": " Shillong"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72671,
    "questionText": " Insects that can transmit diseases to human are referred to as which name?",
    "answerText": " Vectors"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72672,
    "questionText": " Which craftsmanship was not practised by the Aryans?",
    "answerText": " Blacksmith"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72673,
    "questionText": " Total number of Postal Zones?",
    "answerText": 8
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72674,
    "questionText": " What is the main constituent of vinegar?",
    "answerText": " Acetic acid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72675,
    "questionText": " Which mammal rolls itself into ball at the time of danger?",
    "answerText": " Hedgehog"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72676,
    "questionText": " In which Photosynthesis occurs?",
    "answerText": " Chloroplast"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72677,
    "questionText": " What is the permissible level of noise in a silent zone at daytime?",
    "answerText": " 75 dB."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72678,
    "questionText": " Where will the winter youth Olympics Games 2016 be held?",
    "answerText": " Lillehammer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72679,
    "questionText": " The tornadoes are very strong tropical cyclones originating in which sea?",
    "answerText": " Caribbean sea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72680,
    "questionText": " What is the intermediate tier of the Panchayati Raj System called?",
    "answerText": " Panchayat Samiti"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72681,
    "questionText": " Which is the smallest water body?",
    "answerText": " Japan Sea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72682,
    "questionText": " Which is a human right as well as a fundamental right under the Constitution of India?",
    "answerText": " Right to Education"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72683,
    "questionText": " If the temperature inside a room is increased; what will be the relative humidity?",
    "answerText": " Decrease"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72684,
    "questionText": " Which is used as a filler in rubber tyres?",
    "answerText": " Carbon black"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72685,
    "questionText": " Which climate best suited for horticulture?",
    "answerText": " Mediterranean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72686,
    "questionText": " The great grammarian Patanjali of ancient India was whose contemporary?",
    "answerText": " Pushyamitra Sunga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72687,
    "questionText": " What is the minimum age required for becoming the Prime Minister of India?",
    "answerText": " 25 years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72688,
    "questionText": " Rajasansi Airport is at?",
    "answerText": " Amritsar; Punjab"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72689,
    "questionText": " How is the standard of living in a country represented?",
    "answerText": " Per capita income"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72690,
    "questionText": " The Lord of Rings The Return of the King won Oscar award in how many categories?",
    "answerText": 11
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72691,
    "questionText": " On the 21st June; the day light is seen at the North Pole for how many hours?",
    "answerText": " 24 hrs."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72692,
    "questionText": " For which sport is the Val Barker Cup awarded in the Olympic Games?",
    "answerText": " Boxing"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72693,
    "questionText": " Which country has hosted the Asian Games for maximum number of times?",
    "answerText": " Thailand"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72694,
    "questionText": " Who has written the famous book ‘Mankind and Mother Earth?",
    "answerText": " Bertrand Russell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72695,
    "questionText": " Theosophist; educationist and Indian’ national leader’. To whom is this description?",
    "answerText": " Annie Besant"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72696,
    "questionText": " Planning in India derives its objectives from which policy?",
    "answerText": " Directive Principles of State policy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72697,
    "questionText": " Which oceans does not have a north south submarine ridge?",
    "answerText": " Pacific ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72698,
    "questionText": " In which does the subject of Co-operative Societies fall?",
    "answerText": " Concurrent List"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72699,
    "questionText": " Which transition metal is in liquid state?",
    "answerText": " Mercury"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72700,
    "questionText": " Which sea in without a coast line?",
    "answerText": " Saragossa sea"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72701,
    "questionText": " What is the average fat content in buffalow milk?",
    "answerText": 0.072
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72702,
    "questionText": " Which metal is non toxic in nature?",
    "answerText": " Gold"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72703,
    "questionText": " Who appoints the Chairman of the UPSC?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72704,
    "questionText": " In which part was the Nagar style of architecture develop mostly?",
    "answerText": " South India"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72705,
    "questionText": " Entamoeba histolytica is found in which part of man?",
    "answerText": " Intestine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72706,
    "questionText": " Uplift of the backward classes was the main programme of which famay?",
    "answerText": " Satyashodhak Samaj"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72707,
    "questionText": " Ictheologists study what?",
    "answerText": " Fish"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72708,
    "questionText": " Which Judge of the Supreme Court was unsuccessfully sought to be impeached?",
    "answerText": " Justice Ramaswami"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72709,
    "questionText": " What is the study of the interaction of antigens and antibodies called?",
    "answerText": " Serology"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72710,
    "questionText": " Manav Seva Award has been instituted in the memory of which person?",
    "answerText": " Rajiv Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72711,
    "questionText": " In which place was Asia’s first Export Processing Zone (EPZ) set up?",
    "answerText": " Kanada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72712,
    "questionText": " How many High Courts in India have jurisdiction over more than one State (Union Territories not included)?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72713,
    "questionText": " The Upanishads were translated into Persian by the orders of which ruler?",
    "answerText": " Dara Shikoh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72714,
    "questionText": " Which decade is celebrated as First United Nations Decade for the Eradication of Poverty?",
    "answerText": " 1997-2006"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72715,
    "questionText": " The World Cup Cricket Twenty-20 title in the 2012 was won by why country?",
    "answerText": " Australia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72716,
    "questionText": " ‘Parsec’ is the unit of measurement of which distance?",
    "answerText": " Astronomical distance"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72717,
    "questionText": " Who said; “Ram and Rahim are the two different name of the same God”?",
    "answerText": " Kabir"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72718,
    "questionText": " Most of the digestion occur in which part of alimentory canal of man?",
    "answerText": " Small intestine"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72719,
    "questionText": " Starch iodide paper is used to test for the presence of which agent?",
    "answerText": " Oxidising agent"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72720,
    "questionText": " Who is the only cricketer to score two successive centuries in a World Cup?",
    "answerText": " Rahul Dravid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72721,
    "questionText": " When is Right to Know Day (Right To Know Day net) observed?",
    "answerText": " 28-Sep-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72722,
    "questionText": " Which site; where Ashokan pillars exist; has the bull capital?",
    "answerText": " Rampurva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72723,
    "questionText": " Which was the gas which had leaked out of Union Carbide factory in Bhopal?",
    "answerText": " Methyl isocynate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72724,
    "questionText": " To which veda does Ayurveda owe its origin?",
    "answerText": " Yajurveda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72725,
    "questionText": " India won the last Hockey Olympic Gold in which year?",
    "answerText": " 1980; Moscow"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72726,
    "questionText": " Which European country is the guarantor of Bank of Central African States?",
    "answerText": " France"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72727,
    "questionText": " Deficiency of which vitamin cause knock-knee; bow legs and pigeon chest in children?",
    "answerText": " Vitamin D"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72728,
    "questionText": " What is the position of India in terms of production of coal?",
    "answerText": " Fourth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72729,
    "questionText": " The boundary between North and South Korea is marked by which line?",
    "answerText": " 38th Parallel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72730,
    "questionText": " The Government of India has decided to declare which river as ‘National River’?",
    "answerText": " Ganga"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72731,
    "questionText": " The period of rotation and Period of Revolution of the Moon are the same and it is?",
    "answerText": " 29 1/2days."
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72732,
    "questionText": " When is the ‘National Science Day’ celebrated in India?",
    "answerText": " 28-Feb-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72733,
    "questionText": " Finance Commission consists of how many members?",
    "answerText": " A Chairman and three other members"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72734,
    "questionText": " Where did India play its 1st one day international match?",
    "answerText": " Headingley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72735,
    "questionText": " Who was the first General-Secretary of the Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": " Dadabhai Naoroji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72736,
    "questionText": " In whom the executive authority of the Union is vested by the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72737,
    "questionText": " Which was the first woman film star nominated/ elected to the Rajya Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Nargis Dutt"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72738,
    "questionText": " Which type of soils have a marked capacity to retain water?",
    "answerText": " Regur soil"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72739,
    "questionText": " Where are the Postaz temperate grassland?",
    "answerText": " Hungary"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72740,
    "questionText": " Whose advert slogan was You press the button we do the rest?",
    "answerText": " Kodak"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72741,
    "questionText": " Only dead people can be on US postage stamps except who?",
    "answerText": " Astronauts"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72742,
    "questionText": " How many time in a year Sun shines vertically on the equator?",
    "answerText": " Twice a year"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72743,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Indian woman to scale the Mount Everest?",
    "answerText": " Bachendri Pal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72744,
    "questionText": " What percentage of water is lost during transpiration?",
    "answerText": 0.0399
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72745,
    "questionText": " Which element is responsible for blue baby syndrome?",
    "answerText": " Nitrate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72746,
    "questionText": " Which is the first Indian woman to reach Olympic finals in individual track events?",
    "answerText": " P. T. Usha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72747,
    "questionText": " Appetite and satiety centres of brain; where are present in?",
    "answerText": " Hypothalmus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72748,
    "questionText": " Who is a legal advisor of the State Government as provided by the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Advocate General"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72749,
    "questionText": " Who organised Ashwamedha Yajna?",
    "answerText": " Samudragupta"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72750,
    "questionText": " When is International Literacy Day; recognized by the UN observed?",
    "answerText": " 8-Sep-2017"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72751,
    "questionText": " Which post does the Constitution of India not mention?",
    "answerText": " The Deputy Prime Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72752,
    "questionText": " How many States are required to ratify certain Amendments to the Constitution?",
    "answerText": " Not less than half the number"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72753,
    "questionText": " Lakshadweep Islands are the product of which creature?",
    "answerText": " Reef formation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72754,
    "questionText": " What is the energy of the winds and the waves?",
    "answerText": " Kinetic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72755,
    "questionText": " By which is National income of India compiled?",
    "answerText": " Central Statistical Organisation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72756,
    "questionText": " Which Governor General had entertained Ranjit Singh with great honour at Ropar?",
    "answerText": " William Bentich"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72757,
    "questionText": " Who became the first Indian to take 16 wickets in a single test match?",
    "answerText": " Narendra Hirwani"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72758,
    "questionText": " Which region experiences three cropping season for rice in India (Rice Bowl of India)?",
    "answerText": " Brahmaputra valley"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72759,
    "questionText": " Because of which factor; clouds do not precipitate in deserts?",
    "answerText": " Low humidity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72760,
    "questionText": " Which Animal is also known as ‘Portuguese man of war’?",
    "answerText": " Physalia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72761,
    "questionText": " Bahadur Singh is a distinguished athlete of which game?",
    "answerText": " Athletics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72762,
    "questionText": " During the reign of emperor was the artillery most perfect and numerous?",
    "answerText": " Aurangzeb"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72763,
    "questionText": " The Eastern Coast of India is known by which name?",
    "answerText": " Coromandal Coast"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72764,
    "questionText": " Who was the famous Indo-Greek king who embraced Buddhism?",
    "answerText": " Menander"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72765,
    "questionText": " What is reduction of oxide with carbon at high temperature called?",
    "answerText": " Smelting"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72766,
    "questionText": " To whom are the Ministers individually responsible?",
    "answerText": " The President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72767,
    "questionText": " Who has won the most Oscars?",
    "answerText": " Walt Disney"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72768,
    "questionText": " What is the main cause of extinction of species from tropics?",
    "answerText": " Deforestation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72769,
    "questionText": " Which compound is known as white vitriol?",
    "answerText": " ZnSO4 7H2 O"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72770,
    "questionText": " Which presents the most significant feature of Indus Valley Civilization?",
    "answerText": " Burnt brick buildings"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72771,
    "questionText": " Epistemology is the study of what?",
    "answerText": " Knowledge"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72772,
    "questionText": " Which are the “Horn of Africa”?",
    "answerText": " Ethiopia; Djibouti; Somalia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72773,
    "questionText": " Which is the largest Committee of the Parliament?",
    "answerText": " The Estimates Committee"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72774,
    "questionText": " Which is adapted to grow in dry places?",
    "answerText": " Xerophytes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72775,
    "questionText": " Israel has common borders with which countries?",
    "answerText": " Lebanon; Syria; Turkey and Jordan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72776,
    "questionText": " Which is not plantation crop?",
    "answerText": " Sugarcane"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72777,
    "questionText": " Where did the Pallava kings make of rock-cut temples?",
    "answerText": " Mahabalipuram"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72778,
    "questionText": " Where can you find London bridge today?",
    "answerText": " USA ( Arizona )"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72779,
    "questionText": " What minimum number of non-zero non-collinear vectors is required to produce a zero vector?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72780,
    "questionText": " Pakistan which rejoined the Commonwealth; had pulled itself out it in which year?",
    "answerText": 1972
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72781,
    "questionText": " Which dynasty was ruling over North India at the time of Alexander’s invasion?",
    "answerText": " Nanda"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72782,
    "questionText": " How can one can distinguish a telescope from a microscope?",
    "answerText": " By observing size of the lens"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72783,
    "questionText": " Which rays are most penetrating?",
    "answerText": " y-rays"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72784,
    "questionText": " By which algae is Nitrogen fixation done?",
    "answerText": " Blue-green algae"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72785,
    "questionText": " Which treated as artificial currency?",
    "answerText": " SDR"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72786,
    "questionText": " Which metal is extracted by thermal reduction process?",
    "answerText": " Copper"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72787,
    "questionText": " The ‘Grand Trunk Road’ connects which cities?",
    "answerText": " Kolkata and Amritsar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72788,
    "questionText": " Which is the river with highest tidal bore in India?",
    "answerText": " Hoogli"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72789,
    "questionText": " In the short run; a producer;’ how long continues his production?",
    "answerText": " Fixed cost"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72790,
    "questionText": " The longest circle which can be drawn on the earth’s surface passes through where?",
    "answerText": " Equator"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72791,
    "questionText": " The International Court of Justice was established in which year?",
    "answerText": 1946
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72792,
    "questionText": " By whom is the conditions of service and tenure of the Election Commissioner prescribed?",
    "answerText": " Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72793,
    "questionText": " Under which Sultan; Khalisa land increased considerably?",
    "answerText": " Alauddin Khilji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72794,
    "questionText": " Which city lies to the western most longitudes?",
    "answerText": " Jaipur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72795,
    "questionText": " Which is an example of Mauryan art?",
    "answerText": " Bull capital; Rampurva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72796,
    "questionText": " What is the distance of Milky way?",
    "answerText": " 105 light years"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72797,
    "questionText": " What are soaps?",
    "answerText": " Sodium or potassium salts of heavier fatty acids"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72798,
    "questionText": " During which reign was Buddhism split up' into the Hinayana and Mahayana sects at the Buddhist Council?",
    "answerText": " Kanishka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72799,
    "questionText": " Name of S. Chandrashekhar is associated with which subject?",
    "answerText": " Astrophysics"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72800,
    "questionText": " During whose Viceroyalty; Queen Victoria was crowned with ‘Kaiser-i-Hind’ in Delhi Durbar?",
    "answerText": " Lytton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72801,
    "questionText": " In which year was Panchayati Raj started in the country?",
    "answerText": 1959
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72802,
    "questionText": " The headquarters of the International Red Cross is situated in which city?",
    "answerText": " Geneva"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72803,
    "questionText": " Which is the phylum that includes exclusively marine animal?",
    "answerText": " Echinodermata"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72804,
    "questionText": " Who pioneered Khilafat Movement?",
    "answerText": " Ali Brothers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72805,
    "questionText": " Which date is known as ‘Diabetes Day’?",
    "answerText": " 14th November"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72806,
    "questionText": " What is the principal source of revenue to the State Government in India?",
    "answerText": " Sales Tax"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72807,
    "questionText": " The Union Territories get representation in which house?",
    "answerText": " Both Houses of Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72808,
    "questionText": " The distribution of seats of the Parliament are based on which census?",
    "answerText": 1971
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72809,
    "questionText": " In which of the Five Year Plans; preference was given to the weaker sections of the society?",
    "answerText": " Fifth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72810,
    "questionText": " Which blood vessel bringing blood into Bowman’s capsule?",
    "answerText": " Afferent arteriole"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72811,
    "questionText": " Which book is entitled as ‘Bible of Communism’?",
    "answerText": " Das Kapital"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72812,
    "questionText": " Chocolates can be bad for health because of a high content of which element?",
    "answerText": " Nickel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72813,
    "questionText": " The wavelength of X-rays is of the order of how many angstrom?",
    "answerText": " Angstrom"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72814,
    "questionText": " What did Robert Ballard discover in 1985?",
    "answerText": " The Titanic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72815,
    "questionText": " Longest bone found in which part of human body?",
    "answerText": " Thigh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72816,
    "questionText": " Rigveda is divided into 10 books. Which books are the oldest?",
    "answerText": " Second and seventh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72817,
    "questionText": " Which hormone is injected into cow and buffalow during milking?",
    "answerText": " Oxytocin"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72818,
    "questionText": " With what subject do the Articles of the Constitution of India deal?",
    "answerText": " Citizenship"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72819,
    "questionText": " Which first Indian leader to undergo imprisonment in 1882?",
    "answerText": " C. Vijiaraghavachari"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72820,
    "questionText": " The anti-malarial drug Quinine is made from a plant. Which is that plant?",
    "answerText": " Cinchona"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72821,
    "questionText": " The Himalayan mountain system belongs to which mountains?",
    "answerText": " Fold mountains"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72822,
    "questionText": " Which is the branch of agriculture concerned with the production of crops?",
    "answerText": " Agronomy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72823,
    "questionText": " Which Gupta ruler defeated the Huna ruler; Mihirakula?",
    "answerText": " Yasodharman"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72824,
    "questionText": " Mosses and Lichens are the characteristic vegetation of which region?",
    "answerText": " Tundra region"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72825,
    "questionText": " The Varansi Kanyakumari National Highway is called which national highway?",
    "answerText": " NH 7"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72826,
    "questionText": " Which European country is divided into areas called Cantons?",
    "answerText": " Switzerland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72827,
    "questionText": " Who is most famous for the establishment of an elaborate system of municipal administration?",
    "answerText": " Chandragupta Maurya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72828,
    "questionText": " What is the duration of a normal one half of a Hockey match?",
    "answerText": " 30 min"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72829,
    "questionText": " Which art style combines Indian and Greek feature?",
    "answerText": " Gandhar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72830,
    "questionText": " Who was the ruler of medieval India who is credited with the building of the Grand Trunk Road?",
    "answerText": " Sher Shah Suri"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72831,
    "questionText": " The food material in fungi is stored in which form?",
    "answerText": " Glycogen"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72832,
    "questionText": " Where has the use of plough been evidenced?",
    "answerText": " Kalibangan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72833,
    "questionText": " When Akbar surrounded Chittor fort; who saved it for four months?",
    "answerText": " Jaimal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72834,
    "questionText": " The Indian Football team made its first appearance at Olympics in?",
    "answerText": 1948
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72835,
    "questionText": " Who authored the Tamil epic 'Silappadikaram'?",
    "answerText": " Ilango"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72836,
    "questionText": " By whom was the city of Agra founded in 1504?",
    "answerText": " Sikandar Lodi"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72837,
    "questionText": " Who fixes the salaries and the allowances of the Speaker of Lok Sabha?",
    "answerText": " Parliament"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72838,
    "questionText": " Where did Alexander die?",
    "answerText": " Babylon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72839,
    "questionText": " Which celestial body besides earth bear; The Sea of Tranquility’ and The Ocean of Storms’?",
    "answerText": " Moon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72840,
    "questionText": " The ordinances issued by the Governor are subject to approval by which office?",
    "answerText": " State Legislature"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72841,
    "questionText": " What is the most satisfactory method for separating sugars?",
    "answerText": " Chromatography"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72842,
    "questionText": " Which of the following carbohydrates is most abundant in nature?",
    "answerText": " Cellulose"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72843,
    "questionText": " From the evolutionary point of view; which is the most primitive animal?",
    "answerText": " Turtle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72844,
    "questionText": " Person is called ‘Desert Fox’?",
    "answerText": " Gen. Rommel"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72845,
    "questionText": " What is the mean of Epigraphy?",
    "answerText": " The study of inscriptions"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72846,
    "questionText": " By whom was Shuddhi movement (conversion of non-Hindus to Hinduism) started?",
    "answerText": " Swami Dayanand Saraswati"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72847,
    "questionText": " Who long do the World Bank and IMF give respectively?",
    "answerText": " Long term and short term credits"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72848,
    "questionText": " By which number the quality of gasoline’ sample is determined?",
    "answerText": " By its octane number"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72849,
    "questionText": " Which vitamin is generally excreted by humans in urine?",
    "answerText": " Vitamin C"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72850,
    "questionText": " Which is the highest grade of coal whose surface is shining and has the highest calorific value?",
    "answerText": " Anthracite"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72851,
    "questionText": " Healing of wounds is hastened by which vitamin?",
    "answerText": " C"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72852,
    "questionText": " In ancient India; Nalanda University was a great centre for the study of which religion?",
    "answerText": " Mahayana Buddhism"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72853,
    "questionText": " Who was the daughter of Emperor Aurangzeb?",
    "answerText": " Zebunnisa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72854,
    "questionText": " What does Gobar gas contains mainly?",
    "answerText": " Methane"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72855,
    "questionText": " Which was the first State to become bifurcated after independence?",
    "answerText": " Madras"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72856,
    "questionText": " Among the Union Territories which has the highest literacy rate?",
    "answerText": " Lakshadweep"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72857,
    "questionText": " How many centuries in Tests did Sunil Gavaskar bag when he retired?",
    "answerText": 34
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72858,
    "questionText": " When Babur invaded India who was the ruler of Vijayanagara empire in South India?",
    "answerText": " Krishna Deva Raya"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72859,
    "questionText": " Formation of pot holes in river beds is an example of thing?",
    "answerText": " Corrosion"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72860,
    "questionText": " Which silver coins Issued by the Guptas?",
    "answerText": " Rupayaka"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72861,
    "questionText": " Which connects the ocean floor level with the continental level?",
    "answerText": " Continental slope"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72862,
    "questionText": " What is the quantity that remains unchanged in a transformer?",
    "answerText": " Frequency"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72863,
    "questionText": " For how many month can the proclamation of emergency at the first instance be restricted?",
    "answerText": " 6 months"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72864,
    "questionText": " Who appoints the Governor of Jammu and Kashmir?",
    "answerText": " President"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72865,
    "questionText": " Which set contains foods rich in carbohydrates?",
    "answerText": " Banana; potato and rice"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72866,
    "questionText": " What is the amount of actual water vapour of air?",
    "answerText": " Absolute humidity"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72867,
    "questionText": " In which season is the frequency of tropical cyclones in the Bay of Bengal maximum?",
    "answerText": " After summer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72868,
    "questionText": " Indian Institute of Naturopathy and Yogic Science is located at which city?",
    "answerText": " Lucknow"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72869,
    "questionText": " Which instrument meant for measuring the rate of respiration?",
    "answerText": " Respirometer"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72870,
    "questionText": " In case a President dies while in office; for how many months can the Vice-President act as President?",
    "answerText": " 6 months"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72871,
    "questionText": " Between which a government is federal or unitary on the basis of relations?",
    "answerText": " Centre and States"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72872,
    "questionText": " Which soils developed on transported sediments?",
    "answerText": " Lithosols"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72873,
    "questionText": " Which European were the last to come- to pre-independence India as traders?",
    "answerText": " French"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72874,
    "questionText": " What are tropical cyclones of the Bay of Bengal usually called?",
    "answerText": " Typhoons"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72875,
    "questionText": " How many States of the U.S.A. are not attached to its mainland?",
    "answerText": " Two"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72876,
    "questionText": " Who was the political guru of Gandhiji?",
    "answerText": " Gopal Krishna Gokhale"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72877,
    "questionText": " Which current is produced by upwelling of cold water off the coast of Chile and Peru?",
    "answerText": " Humboldt current"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72878,
    "questionText": " If a place is located at 20°N; 80°E in which continents does it lie?",
    "answerText": " Asia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72879,
    "questionText": " With which amendment act has Panchayati Raj received constitutional status?",
    "answerText": " 73rd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72880,
    "questionText": " Who directed the world famous film ‘The Gandhi’?",
    "answerText": " Richard Attenborough"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72881,
    "questionText": " What is termed as the period of high inflation and low economic growth?",
    "answerText": " Stagflation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72882,
    "questionText": " How is the National Development Council?",
    "answerText": " Nonpolitical body"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72883,
    "questionText": " What does Dear Money Policy imply?",
    "answerText": " High interest rates"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72884,
    "questionText": " Why does the western coast of India receive very high rainfall in summer mainly?",
    "answerText": " Due to western Ghats"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72885,
    "questionText": " In which the formation of magma along the bedding plane results?",
    "answerText": " Sill"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72886,
    "questionText": " By whom was Electron first identified?",
    "answerText": " J. J. Thomson"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72887,
    "questionText": " When was the Reserve Bank of India taken over by the Government?",
    "answerText": 1948
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72888,
    "questionText": " At where an example of Chola architecture can be seen?",
    "answerText": " Tanjore"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72889,
    "questionText": " Which Article of the Constitution of India makes a specific mention of Village Panchayats?",
    "answerText": " Article 40"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72890,
    "questionText": " Which countries were involved in 100 year war?",
    "answerText": " England and France"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72891,
    "questionText": " Next to Hindi; which is the language spoken by the largest number of people in the Indian sub-continent?",
    "answerText": " Bengali"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72892,
    "questionText": " Forest policy of govt. aims to bring what percentage of total area; under forest?",
    "answerText": 0.0033
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72893,
    "questionText": " “Man without society is either a beast or a God”. Who said this?",
    "answerText": " Aristotle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72894,
    "questionText": " Sex determination of child is done by whose chromosome?",
    "answerText": " Father"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72895,
    "questionText": " Which soil is most suited for tea plantation?",
    "answerText": " Acidic"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72896,
    "questionText": " In which year; some more commercial banks in addition to the first lot of 141 were nationalised in India?",
    "answerText": 1980
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72897,
    "questionText": " How many pair of heart is found in an earthworm?",
    "answerText": " Four"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72898,
    "questionText": " Why are the Canals in Western Europe are mainly used?",
    "answerText": " For inland navigation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72899,
    "questionText": " Which archaeologist initially discovered the Mohenjodaro site of the Indus Valley Civilization?",
    "answerText": " Rakhal Das Banerji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72900,
    "questionText": " Parthanogenesis is seen generally in which fruit?",
    "answerText": " Grapes"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72901,
    "questionText": " Who was the greatest Buddhist commentator of the Buddhist canonical literature?",
    "answerText": " Ashvaqhosha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72902,
    "questionText": " In Which kind of organisms is the phenomenon found wherein the female kills the male after copulation?",
    "answerText": " Spider"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72903,
    "questionText": " When is International women’s Day recognized by the UN observed?",
    "answerText": " March"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72904,
    "questionText": " Which Chief Justice of India has acted as President of India?",
    "answerText": " M. Hidayatullah"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72905,
    "questionText": " Which English Poet finished writing the epic poem ‘Paradise Lost’?",
    "answerText": " John Milton"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72906,
    "questionText": " Radioactive distintegration of uranium ultimately results in which formation?",
    "answerText": " Lead"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72907,
    "questionText": " What is the Biological death of a patient?",
    "answerText": " Death of tissues of the brain"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72908,
    "questionText": " Who was the first Indian woman President of the Indian National Congress?",
    "answerText": " Sarojini Naidu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72909,
    "questionText": " What function is specifically prescribed by the Constitution for the vice-President of India?",
    "answerText": " Chairman of Rajya Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72910,
    "questionText": " The Maratha power reached its zenith during which Peshwaship?",
    "answerText": " Balaji II"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72911,
    "questionText": " Which river originates at Amarkantak?",
    "answerText": " Narmada"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72912,
    "questionText": " What is the basic attribute of a formal organization?",
    "answerText": " Rules and regulations"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72913,
    "questionText": " A car is running on a road at a uniform speed of 60 km/hr. What is the net resultant force on the car?",
    "answerText": " Equal to zero"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72914,
    "questionText": " Which is used in storage batteries?",
    "answerText": " Lead"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72915,
    "questionText": " Which is the suthernmost city?",
    "answerText": " Raipur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72916,
    "questionText": " How much the equatorial circumference is greater than the polar circumference?",
    "answerText": " Approximately 68 km"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72917,
    "questionText": " Strait of Florida runs in between which water bodies?",
    "answerText": " Atlantic Ocean and Gulf of Mexico"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72918,
    "questionText": " Who was the ruler of Chittor; when Alauddin Khilji attacked and conquered it in 1303 A.D.?",
    "answerText": " Rana Ratan Singh"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72919,
    "questionText": " Why was the Indus Valley Civilization Non-Aryan?",
    "answerText": " Because it was urban"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72920,
    "questionText": " In which ocean are Hawaiian islands are located?",
    "answerText": " North Pacific Ocean"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72921,
    "questionText": " How is the Relative humidity of the atmosphere directly affected?",
    "answerText": " Change in atmospheric temperature"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72922,
    "questionText": " Which current is produced by upwelling of water off the coast of Chile and Peru?",
    "answerText": " Humboldt Current"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72923,
    "questionText": " Which lake lies in the ‘Dead heart of Australia’?",
    "answerText": " Eyre"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72924,
    "questionText": " The images of which deities are in the temple of Angkorvat?",
    "answerText": " Hindu deities"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72925,
    "questionText": " Who was the great Hindu law-giver?",
    "answerText": " Manu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72926,
    "questionText": " What is Crop rotation?",
    "answerText": " Growing different crops-in succession"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72927,
    "questionText": " Eric Arthur Blaire was the real name of which author?",
    "answerText": " George Orwell"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72928,
    "questionText": " What was the capital of Hoyasals?",
    "answerText": " Dwarasamudra"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72929,
    "questionText": " What is the part of the Constitution that reflects the mind and ideals of the framers?",
    "answerText": " Preamble"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72930,
    "questionText": " Which is the deepest lake?",
    "answerText": " Lake Baikal"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72931,
    "questionText": " How many gold medals did India win at the XIth Asian Games?",
    "answerText": " One"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72932,
    "questionText": " Who succeeded Siraj-ud-Daulah as Nawab of Bengal after the Battle of Plassey?",
    "answerText": " Mir Jafar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72933,
    "questionText": " The sun is visible a little before the actual sunrise because of which reaction?",
    "answerText": " Atmospheric refraction"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72934,
    "questionText": " Who has become the first Indian to score a triple century in Tests?",
    "answerText": " Virender Sehwag"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72935,
    "questionText": " Silver is obtained from the lead & Zinc ares of Zawar mines in which city?",
    "answerText": " Udaipur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72936,
    "questionText": " What job does an Oikologiost do?",
    "answerText": " Housekeeper"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72937,
    "questionText": " Which winds are flowing from sub tropical high pressure to sub polar low pressure?",
    "answerText": " Westerlies"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72938,
    "questionText": " Citizenship provisions are enshrined in the Constitution in which article?",
    "answerText": " Part II; Articles -11"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72939,
    "questionText": " Which rocks is transformed into marble?",
    "answerText": " Limestone"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72940,
    "questionText": " Which struggley of Mahatma Gandhi was related to Industrial worker?",
    "answerText": " Ahmedabad Struggle"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72941,
    "questionText": " Which is a block mountain?",
    "answerText": " Vosges"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72942,
    "questionText": " Which cell organelle is semi-permeable?",
    "answerText": " Plasma membrane"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72943,
    "questionText": " The Centre-State financial distribution takes place on the recommendation by which ministry?",
    "answerText": " Finance Minister"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72944,
    "questionText": " Which was India’s first mobile offshore drilling platform?",
    "answerText": " Sagar Samrat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72945,
    "questionText": " Which oceanic tidal wave that moves upto 200 MPH and is up to 1000 feet high?",
    "answerText": " Tsunami"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72946,
    "questionText": " Ethylene reacts with sulphur monochloride to form which gas?",
    "answerText": " Mustard gas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72947,
    "questionText": " There is a submarine ridge in the Bay of Bengal. What is it called?",
    "answerText": " Ninety east ridge"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72948,
    "questionText": " Image of object is formed on which part of eye?",
    "answerText": " Retina"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72949,
    "questionText": " What was the most important feature of the Government of India Act of 1919?",
    "answerText": " Introduction of Dyarchy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72950,
    "questionText": " രക്തത്തിലടങ്ങിയിരിക്കുന്ന ലോഹം? ",
    "answerText": " ഇരുമ്പ് "
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72951,
    "questionText": " Who was teh most famous court-poet (in Hindi literature) of Akbar?",
    "answerText": " Abdur Rahim-Khan-i-Khanan"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72952,
    "questionText": " When was EXIM Bank set-up?",
    "answerText": 1982
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72953,
    "questionText": " The United Nations declared 2001 as which International Year?",
    "answerText": " International Year of Volunteers"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72954,
    "questionText": " By whom is the Speaker of the Lok Sabha is elected?",
    "answerText": " All the members of Lok Sabha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72955,
    "questionText": " Which processe is used to remove reducible oxides from the metal?",
    "answerText": " Poling"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72956,
    "questionText": " Which is east of the Andaman and Nicobar Islands?",
    "answerText": " Indonesia"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72957,
    "questionText": " On which base is the India’s wage policy?",
    "answerText": " Cost of living"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72958,
    "questionText": " Which major chemical compound found in human kidney stones?",
    "answerText": " Calcium oxalate"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72959,
    "questionText": " How many Nobel Prizes have been awarded so far to Indian citizens?",
    "answerText": 3
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72960,
    "questionText": " Which element has the lowest electron affinity?",
    "answerText": " Argon"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72961,
    "questionText": " Thermal radiations are electromagnetic wave belonging to which region?",
    "answerText": " Infrared region"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72962,
    "questionText": " Kudremukh hills known for iron ore deposits is situated in which place?",
    "answerText": " Chickmaglur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72963,
    "questionText": " Which war was ended by the Treaty of Madras?",
    "answerText": " First Mysore war"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72964,
    "questionText": " What was the earlier name of the WTO?",
    "answerText": " GAD"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72965,
    "questionText": " Which was the lady to win the Wimbledon singles title successfully nine times?",
    "answerText": " Martina Navratilova"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72966,
    "questionText": " Which newspaper was published in Bengali language?",
    "answerText": " Jugantar"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72967,
    "questionText": " Which flim was made by Satyajit Ray for Children?",
    "answerText": " Sonar Killa"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72968,
    "questionText": " The mapping of which part of earth is most difficult?",
    "answerText": " Interior of the Earth"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72969,
    "questionText": " By which a mixture of sand and naphthalene can be separated?",
    "answerText": " Sublimation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72970,
    "questionText": " Which is the place that has the longest day and the shortest night on 22nd December;?",
    "answerText": " Melbourne"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72971,
    "questionText": " In which place is the headquarters of the North-Eastern Railway located?",
    "answerText": " Gorakhpur"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72972,
    "questionText": " With rise of boiling point of a water; what will be the latent heat of steam?",
    "answerText": " Decreases"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72973,
    "questionText": " When do the Sea breeze blow?",
    "answerText": " Day from sea to land"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72974,
    "questionText": " Who was the last ruler of the Tughlaq dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate?",
    "answerText": " Nasir-ud-din-Mahmud"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72975,
    "questionText": " The Vijay Satambha (Tower of Victory) at Chittor was built by which ruler?",
    "answerText": " Rana Kumbha"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72976,
    "questionText": " Who is the longest serving Chief Minister in India?",
    "answerText": " Jyoti Basu"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72977,
    "questionText": " According to which system are the members of the Rajya Sabha elected?",
    "answerText": " Single Transferable Vote System"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72978,
    "questionText": " By whom was Swaraj as a national demand first made?",
    "answerText": " Dadabhai Naoroji"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72979,
    "questionText": " By whom is the parliament’s expenditure is controlled?",
    "answerText": " Comptroller and Auditor General"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72980,
    "questionText": " Which winds are predominantly seasonal winds?",
    "answerText": " Monsoon winds"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72981,
    "questionText": " Which type of forest covers the maximum area in India?",
    "answerText": " Tropical moist deciduous forest"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72982,
    "questionText": " For which is the northern blot technique used for the detection?",
    "answerText": " RNA"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72983,
    "questionText": " Which inscription mentions Pulkesin II’s military success against Harshavardhana?",
    "answerText": " Aihole Inscription"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72984,
    "questionText": " The World Food Prize is given by which organisation/world bodie?",
    "answerText": " Kraft general foods"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72985,
    "questionText": " According to which article untouchability is abolished and its practice is punishable?",
    "answerText": " Article 17"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72986,
    "questionText": " From which sector does the highest sector wise contribution to gross domestic saving comes?",
    "answerText": " Household sector"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72987,
    "questionText": " During which time was Gandhara school of art developed?",
    "answerText": " Mauryas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72988,
    "questionText": " By whom were the triratnas were stressed?",
    "answerText": " Mahavira"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72989,
    "questionText": " What is the capitol of Morocco?",
    "answerText": " Rabat"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72990,
    "questionText": " Which Amendment of the Constitution of India deals with the issue of strengthening of the Panchayati Raj?",
    "answerText": " 73rd"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72991,
    "questionText": " The ‘Paditrupputtu’ is a collection of poems in the praise of which king?",
    "answerText": " Chera"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72992,
    "questionText": " Between which the famous Battle of Takkolam in South India was fought?",
    "answerText": " Cholas and Rashtrakutas"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72993,
    "questionText": " By whom was the idea of the Constitution of India first of all given?",
    "answerText": " M. N. Roy"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72994,
    "questionText": " Which Scale is used for recording weather condition?",
    "answerText": " Centigrade"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72995,
    "questionText": " Which planet of the solar system has the longest day?",
    "answerText": " Venus"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72996,
    "questionText": " In which country has maximum damage to the forests been caused by acid rain?",
    "answerText": " Poland"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72997,
    "questionText": " What was Sher Shah’s real name?",
    "answerText": " Farid"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72998,
    "questionText": " Why does the Issue Department of the RBI maintain a against printing of note?",
    "answerText": " Minimum Reserve System"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 72999,
    "questionText": " Rusting of iron is an example of which thing?",
    "answerText": " Slow oxidation"
  },
  {
    "questionNum": 73000,
    "questionText": " How is Share of Direct tax in post economic reform?",
    "answerText": " Increasing"
  }
]